<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<notes>
	<note>As to the judgment of Paris （Alexander）, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 24.25"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 24.25ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Cypria, in Proclus, Chrestom. i. （Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G.
			Kinkel, pp. 16ff.）</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Tro. 924"
			valid="yes">Eur. Tro. 924ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. IA 1290"
			valid="yes">Eur. IA 1290ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hel. 23"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hel. 23ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Andr. 274"
			valid="yes">Eur. And. 274ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Isoc. 10.41"
			valid="yes">Isoc. 10.41</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Lucian, Dial. Deorum 20, Dial. marin. 5</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 93</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 92</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 1.27"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 1.27</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. pp. 65ff., 142ff. (First
			Vatican Mythographer 208; Second Vatican Mythographer 205)</bibl>. The story ran that
		all the gods and goddesses, except Strife, were invited to attend the marriage of Peleus and
		Thetis, and that Strife, out of spite at being overlooked, threw among the wedding guests a
		golden apple inscribed with the words, “Let the fair one take it,” or “The apple for the
		fair.” Three goddesses, Hera, Athena, and Aphrodite, contended for this prize of beauty, and
		Zeus referred the disputants to the judgment of Paris. The intervention of Strife was
		mentioned in the Cypria according to Proclus, but without mention of the golden apple, which
		first appears in late writers, such as Lucian and Hyginus. The offers made by the three
		divine competitors to Paris are recorded with substantial agreement by <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Tro. 924"
			valid="yes">Eur. Tro. 924ff.</bibl>, Isocrates, Lucian, and Apollodorus. Hyginus is also
		in harmony with them, if in his text we read <foreign
			lang="la">fortissimum</foreign> for the <foreign
			lang="la">formissimum</foreign> of the MSS., for which some editors wrongly read <foreign
			lang="la">formosissimum</foreign>. The scene of the judgment of Paris was represented on
		the throne of Apollo at Amyclae and on the chest of Cypselus at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Olympia"
			key="perseus,Olympia">Olympia</placeName> （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 3.8.12"
			valid="yes">Paus. 3.8.12</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 5.19.5"
			valid="yes">Paus. 5.19.5</bibl>）.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 5.59"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 5.59ff.</bibl>, from which we learn that the shipbuilder was a son
		of Tecton, who was a son of Harmon. The names of his father and grandfather indicate, as Dr.
		Leaf observes, that the business had been carried on in the family for three generations.
		Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 97</bibl>.</note>
	<note>The Greek for “to go off” is <foreign
			lang="greek">a)pagagei=n</foreign>, a rare use of <foreign
			lang="greek">a)pa/gein</foreign>, which, however, occurs in the common phrase, <foreign
			lang="greek">a)/page</foreign>,“Be off with you!”</note>
	<note>With this account of the hospitable reception of Paris in <placeName
			authname="perseus,Sparta"
			key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, the departure of Menelaus for <placeName
			authname="tgn,7012056"
			key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>, and the flight of the guilty pair, compare <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus, Chrestom. i., in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p.
			17</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Antehomerica 96-134</bibl>. As to the death of Catreus, the
		maternal grandfather of Menelaus, see above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. 3.2.1"
			valid="yes">Apollod. 3.2.1ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>The voyage of Paris and Helen to <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002861"
			key="tgn,7002861">Sidon</placeName> was known to <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 6.289"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 6.289ff.</bibl>, with the <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. 6.291</bibl>. It was also recorded in the epic
			<title>Cypria</title>, according to Proclus, who says that Paris captured the city （<bibl
			default="NO">Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 18</bibl>）. Yet according
		to <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hdt. 2.117"
			valid="yes">Hdt. 2.117</bibl>, the author of the <title>Cypria</title> described how
		Paris and Helen sailed in three days from <placeName
			authname="perseus,Sparta"
			key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> with a fair wind and a smooth sea. It seems
		therefore that Herodotus and Proclus had different texts of the <title>Cypria</title> before
		them. Dictys Cretensis tells how, driven by the winds to <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000112"
			key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>, Paris sailed with some ships to <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002861"
			key="tgn,7002861">Sidon</placeName>, where he was hospitably entertained by the king,
		but basely requited his hospitality by treacherously murdering his host and plundering the
		palace. In embarking with his booty on his ships, he was attacked by the Sidonians, but,
		after a bloody fight and the loss of two ships, he succeeded in beating off his assailants
		and putting to sea with the rest of his vessels. See <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis i.5</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hel. 31"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hel. 31-51</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hel. 582"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hel. 582ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hel. 669"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hel. 669ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. El. 1280"
			valid="yes">Eur. El. 1280ff.</bibl> In the <title>Helen</title> the dramatist says that
		Hera, angry with Paris for preferring Aphrodite to her, fashioned a phantom Helen which he
		wedded, while the real Helen was transported by Hermes to <placeName
			authname="tgn,7016833"
			key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> and committed to the care of Proteus. In the
			<title>Electra</title> the poet says that it was Zeus who sent a phantom Helen to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, in order to stir up strife and provoke bloodshed
		among men. A different account is given by <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hdt. 2.112"
			valid="yes">Hdt. 2.112-120</bibl>. According to him, Paris carried the real Helen to <placeName
			authname="tgn,7016833"
			key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, but there king Proteus, indignant at the crime of
		which Paris had been guilty, banished him from <placeName
			authname="tgn,7016833"
			key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> and detained Helen in safekeeping until her true
		husband, Menelaus, came and fetched her away. Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Philostratus, Vit. Apollon. iv.16</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Antehomerica 147ff.</bibl> Later writers accepted this view,
		adding that instead of the real Helen, whom he kept, Proteus conjured up by magic art a
		phantom Helen, which he gave to Paris to carry away with him to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. See <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 113</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 1.651"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 1.651</bibl> and <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="ii.592"> ii.592</bibl>. So far as we know, the poet Stesichorus in the sixth century
		before our era was the first to broach the theory that Helen at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, for whom the Greeks and Trojans fought and died,
		was a mere wraith, while her true self was far away, whether at home in <placeName
			authname="perseus,Sparta"
			key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> or with Proteus in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7016833"
			key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>; for there is nothing to show whether Stesichorus
		shared the opinion that Paris had spirited her away to the East before he returned, with or
		without her, to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. This view the poet propounded by way of an apology
		to Helen for the evil he had spoken of her in a former poem; for having lost the sight of
		his eyes he ascribed the loss to the vengeance of the heroine, and sought to propitiate her
		by formally retracting all the scandals he had bruited about concerning her. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Plat. Phaedrus 243a"
			valid="yes">Plat. Phaedrus 243a-b</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Plat. Rep. 9.586c"
			valid="yes">Plat. Rep. 9.586c</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Isoc. 10.64"
			valid="yes">Isoc. 10.64</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 3.19.13"
			valid="yes">Paus. 3.19.13</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Poetae Lyrici Graeci, ed. Th. Bergk, iii.980ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>As to these oaths, see above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. 3.10.9"
			valid="yes">Apollod. 3.10.9</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the madness which Ulysses feigned in order to escape going to the Trojan war, see <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 18</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Lucian, De domo 30</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Philostratus, Her. xi.2</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 818</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Cicero, De officiis iii.26.97</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 95</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 2.81"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 2.81</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Lactantius Placidus on Statius, Achill. i.93</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. pp. 12, 140ff. (First
			Vatican Mythographer 35; Second Vatican Mythographer 200)</bibl>. The usual story seems
		to have been that to support his pretence of insanity Ulysses yoked an ox and a horse or an
		ass to the plough and sowed salt. While he was busy fertilizing the fields in this fashion,
		the Greek envoys arrived, and Palamedes, seeing through the deception, laid the infant son
		of Ulysses in front of the plough, whereupon the father at once checked the plough and
		betrayed his sanity. However, Lucian agrees with Apollodorus in saying that Palamedes
		threatened the child with his sword, though at the same time, by mentioning the unlike
		animals yoked together, he shows that he had the scene of the ploughing in his mind. His
		description purports to be based on a picture, probably a famous picture of the scene which
		was still exhibited at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Ephesos"
			key="perseus,Ephesos">Ephesus</placeName> in the time of <bibl
			default="NO">Pliny, Nat. Hist. xxxv.129</bibl>. Sophocles wrote a play on the subject,
		called <title>The Mad Ulysses</title>. See <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, vol. ii. pp.
			115ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>The Machiavellian device by which the crafty Ulysses revenged himself on Palamedes for
		forcing him to go to the war is related more fully by a <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Eur. Or. 432</bibl> and <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 105</bibl>. According to the Scholiast, a servant of
		Palamedes was bribed to secrete the forged letter and the gold under his master's bed, where
		they were discovered and treated as damning evidence of treason. According to Hyginus,
		Ulysses had recourse to a still more elaborate stratagem in order to bury the gold in the
		earth under the tent of Palamedes. Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 2.81"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 2.81</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Lactantius Placidus on Statius, Achill. i.93</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. pp. 12, 140ff. (First
			Vatican Mythographer 35; Second Vatican Mythographer 200)</bibl>. An entirely different
		account of the plot against Palamedes is told by <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis ii.15</bibl>. He says that Ulysses and Diomede induced him
		to descend into a well, and then buried him under rocks which they hurled down on the top of
		him.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 11.19"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 11.19ff.</bibl>, who describes only one richly decorated
		breastplate.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Il. 11.20, p. 827</bibl>, who says that, according to
		some people, Cinyras “swore to Menelaus at <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002373"
			key="tgn,7002373">Paphos</placeName> that he would send fifty ships, but he despatched
		only one, and the rest he fashioned of earth and sent them with earthen men in them; thus he
		cunningly evaded his oath by keeping it with an earthenware fleet.” Compare the <bibl
			default="NO">Townley Scholiast on Hom. Il. 11.20, ed. E. Maass （Oxford, 1887）, vol. i.
			p. 378</bibl>. Wagner may be right in supposing that this ruse of the Cyprian king was
		recorded in the epic <title>Cypria</title>, though it is not mentioned in the brief summary
		of the poem compiled by Proclus. See <bibl
			default="NO">R. Wagner, <title>Epitoma Vaticana ex Apollodori Bibliotheca</title>, pp.
			181ff.</bibl> A different account of the Greek embassy to Cinyras is given by <bibl
			default="NO">Alcidamas, Od. 20ff., pp. 181ff., ed. Blass</bibl>. He says that Cinyras
		bribed the Greek envoy Palamedes to relieve him from military service, and that, though he
		promised to send a hundred ships, he sent none at all.</note>
	<note>As to these three women, the Winegrowers （Oinotrophoi, or Oinotropoi） see <bibl
			default="NO">Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, pp. 29ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 570, 581</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Od. vi.164</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Ov. Met. 13.632"
			valid="yes">Ov. Met. 13.632-674</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 3.80"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 3.80</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis i.23</bibl>. Each of the Winegrowers received from
		Dionysus the power of producing the thing from which she derived her name; thus Elais, who
		took her name from <foreign
			lang="greek">e)lai/a</foreign>, “an olive,” could produce olive oil; Spermo, who took
		her name from <foreign
			lang="greek">spe/rma</foreign>, “seed,” could produce corn; and Oeno, who took her name
		from <foreign
			lang="greek">oi)=nos</foreign>, “wine,” could produce wine. According to Apollodorus,
		the women elicited these products from the ground; but according to Ovid and Servius,
		whatever they touched was turned into olive-oil, corn, or wine, as the case might be.
		Possessing these valuable powers, the daughters of Anius were naturally much sought after.
		Their father, a son of Apollo, was king of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delos"
			key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> and at the same time priest of his father Apollo （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Verg. A. 3.80"
			valid="yes">Verg. A. 3.80</bibl>）, and when Aeneas visited the island on his way from <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, the king, with pardonable pride, dwelt on his
		daughters' accomplishments and on the income they had brought him in （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Ov. Met. 13.650"
			valid="yes">Ov. Met. 13.650ff.</bibl>） It is said by Tzetzes that when the Greeks sailed
		for <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> and landed in <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delos"
			key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>, the king, who had received the gift of prophecy
		from his divine sire （<bibl
			default="NO">Diod. 5.62.2</bibl>）, foretold that <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> would not be taken for ten years, and invited them
		to stay with him for nine years, promising that his daughters would find them in food all
		the time. This hospitable offer was apparently not accepted at the moment; but afterwards,
		when the Greeks were encamped before <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, Agamemnon sent for the young women and ordered them
		peremptorily to feed his army. This they did successfully, if we may believe Tzetzes; but,
		to judge by Ovid's account, they found the work of the commissariat too exacting, for he
		says that they took to flight. Being overtaken by their pursuers, they prayed to Dionysus,
		who turned them into white doves. And that, says Servius, is why down to this day it is
		deemed a sin to harm a dove in <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delos"
			key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>. From Tzetzes we learn that the story of these
		prolific damsels was told by Pherecydes and by the author of the epic <title>Cypria</title>,
		from whom Pherecydes may have borrowed it. Stesichorus related how Menelaus and Ulysses went
		to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delos"
			key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> to fetch the daughters of Anius （<bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Od. vi.164</bibl>）. If we may judge from the place which
		the brief mention of these women occupies in the <title>Epitome</title> of Apollodorus, we
		may conjecture that in his full text he described how their services were requisitioned to
		victual the fleet and army assembling at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Aulis"
			key="perseus,Aulis">Aulis</placeName>. The conjecture is confirmed by the statement of
		Dictys Cretensis, that before the Greek army set sail from <placeName
			authname="perseus,Aulis"
			key="perseus,Aulis">Aulis</placeName>, it had received a supply of corn, wine, and other
		provisions from Anius and his daughters. It may have been in order to ensure these supplies
		that Menelaus and Ulysses repaired to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delos"
			key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> for the purpose of securing the persons of the
		women.</note>
	<note>As to list of the Greek forces which mustered at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Aulis"
			key="perseus,Aulis">Aulis</placeName>, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 2.494"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.494-759</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. IA 253"
			valid="yes">Eur. IA 253ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 97</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis i.17</bibl>. The numbers of the ships and leaders recorded
		by Apollodorus do not always tally with those of Homer. For example, he gives the Boeotians
		forty ships, while Homer （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 5.509"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 5.509</bibl>） gives them fifty; and he says that the Phocians had
		four leaders, whereas Homer （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 5.517"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 5.517</bibl>） mentions only two. The question of the catalogue of
		the Greek forces, and its relation to Homer and history, are fully discussed by Dr. Walter
		Leaf in his <bibl
			default="NO"><title>Homer and History</title> （London, 1915）</bibl>. He concludes that
		the catalogue forms no part of the original but was added to it at a later time by a
		patriotic Boeotian for the purpose of glorifying his people by claiming that they played a
		very important part in the Trojan war, although this claim is inconsistent with the
		statement of <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Thuc. 1.12"
			valid="yes">Thuc. 1.12</bibl> that the Boeotians did not migrate into the country
		henceforth known as <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002683"
			key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> until sixty years after the capture of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. I agree with Dr. Leaf in the belief, which he
		energetically maintains in this book, that the Trojan war was not a myth, but a real war,
		“fought out in the place, and at least generally in the manner, described in Homer,” and
		that the principal heroes and heroines recorded by Homer were not “faded gods” but men and
		women of flesh and blood, of whose families and fortunes the memory survived in Greek
		tradition, though no doubt in course of time many mythical traits and incidents gathered
		round them, as they have gathered round the memories of the Hebrew patriarchs, of Alexander
		the Great, of Virgil, and of Charlemagne.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 2.299"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.299-330</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 18</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Cicero, De divinatione ii.30.63-65</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Ov. Met. 12.11"
			valid="yes">Ov. Met. 12.11-23</bibl>.</note>
	<note>No other ancient writer mentions that Achilles was high admiral of the fleet, though as
		son of a sea-goddess he was obviously fitted for the post. Dictys Cretensis, however, tells
		us （<bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis i.16</bibl>） that Achilles shared the command of the ships
		with Ajax and Phoenix, while that of the land forces was divided between Palamedes,
		Diomedes, and Ulysses.</note>
	<note>With the following account of the landing of the Greeks in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7016748"
			key="tgn,7016748">Mysia</placeName> and their encounter with Telephus, compare Proclus,
		in <bibl
			default="NO">Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, pp. 18ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. i.59</bibl>. The accounts of both these writers
		agree, to some extent verbally, with that of Apollodorus and are probably drawn from the
		same source, which may have been the epic <title>Cypria</title> summarized by Proclus. The
		Scholiast tells us that it was Dionysus who caused Telephus to trip over a vine-branch,
		because Telephus had robbed the god of the honours that were his due. The incident is
		alluded to by <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Pind. I. 8"
			valid="yes">Pind. I. 8.48(106)ff.</bibl> The war in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7016748"
			key="tgn,7016748">Mysia</placeName> is narrated in more detail by <bibl
			default="NO">Philostratus, Her. iii.28-36</bibl> and <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis ii.1-7</bibl>. <bibl
			default="NO">Philostratus, Her. 35</bibl> says that the wounded were washed in the
		waters of the hot Ionian springs, which the people of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Smyrna"
			key="perseus,Smyrna">Smyrna</placeName> called the springs of Agamemnon.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 19</bibl>,
		according to whom Achilles, on this return voyage, landed in Scyros and married his youthful
		love Deidamia, daughter of Lycomedes. See above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. 3.13.8"
			valid="yes">Apollod. 3.13.8</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 24.765"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 24.765ff.</bibl>, where Helen at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> says that it was now the twentieth year since she
		had quitted her native land. The words have puzzled the Scholiasts and commentators, but are
		explained by the present passage of Apollodorus.</note>
	<note>This account of how Telephus steered the Greek fleet to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> after being healed of his grievous wound by
		Achilles, is probably derived from the epic <title>Cypria</title>; since it agrees on these
		points with the brief summary of Proclus. See <bibl
			default="NO">Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 19</bibl>. Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. i.59</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis ii.10</bibl>. As to the cure of Telephus's wound by means
		of the rust of the spear, see also <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 101</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Prop. 2.1.63"
			valid="yes">Prop. ii.1.63ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Ovid, Ex Ponto ii.2.6</bibl>. Pliny describes a painting in which Achilles
		was represented scraping the rust from the blade of his spear with a sword into the wound of
		Telephus （<bibl
			default="NO">Pliny, Nat. Hist. xxv.42, xxxiv.152</bibl>）. The spear was the famous one
		which Chiron had bestowed on Peleus, the father of Achilles; the shaft was cut from an
		ash-tree on Mount Pelion, and none of the Greeks at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, except Achilles, could wield it. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 16.140"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 16.140-144</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 19.387"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 19.387-391</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 22.133"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 22.133ff.</bibl> The healing of Telephus's wound by Achilles is
		also reported, though without mention of the spear, by <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis ii.10</bibl>, a <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. i.59</bibl> and a <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Aristoph. Cl. 919</bibl>. The subject was treated by Sophocles
		in a play called <title>The Assembly of the Achaeans</title>, and by Euripides in a play
		called <title>Telephus</title>. See <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson,
			i.94ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"><title>Griechische Dichterfragmente</title>. ii. <title>Lyrische und
				dramatische Fragmente</title>, ed. W. Schubart und U. von Wilamowitz-Moellendorff
			（Berlin, 1907）, pp. 64ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">TGF (Nauck 2nd ed.), pp. 161ff., 579ff.</bibl> Aristophanes ridiculed the
		rags and tatters in which Telephus appeared on the stage in Euripides's play （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aristoph. Ach. 430"
			valid="yes">Aristoph. Acharn. 430ff.</bibl>）. Apollodorus may have had the passage of
		Euripides or the parody of Aristophanes in mind when he describes Telephus as clad in rags.
		The cure of a wound by an application to it of rust from the weapon which inflicted the hurt
		is not to be explained, as Pliny supposed, by any medicinal property inherent in rust as
		such, else the rust from any weapon would serve the purpose. It is clearly a folklore remedy
		based on the principle of sympathetic magic. Similarly Iphiclus was cured of impotence by
		the rust of the same knife which had caused the infirmity. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. 1.9.12"
			valid="yes">Apollod. 1.9.12</bibl>. The proverbial remedy for the bite of a dog “the
		hair of the dog that bit you,” is strictly analogous in principle; for it is not the hair of
		any dog that will work the cure, but only the hair of the particular dog that inflicted the
		bite. Thus we read of a beggar who was bitten by a dog, at the vicarage of Heversham, in
		Westmoreland, and went back to the house to ask for some of the animal's hair to put on the
		wound. See <bibl
			default="NO">W. Henderson, <title>Notes on the Folk-lore of the Northern Counties of
				England</title> （London, 1879）, p. 160, note 1</bibl>. A precisely similar remedy
		for similar hurts appears to be popular in <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000111"
			key="tgn,1000111">China</placeName>; for we hear of a missionary who travelled about the
		province of Canton accompanied by a powerful dog, which bit children in the villages through
		which his master passed; and when a child was bitten, its mother used to run after the
		missionary and beg for a hair from the dog's tail to lay on the child's wound as a remedy.
		See <bibl
			default="NO">N. B. Dennys, <title>The Folklore of China</title> （London and Hongkong,
			1876）, p. 52</bibl>. For more examples of supposed cures based on the principle of
		sympathy between the animal who bites and the person who is bitten, see <bibl
			default="NO">W. Henderson, l.c.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">W. G. Black, <title>Folk-Medicine</title> （London, 1883）, pp. 50ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">W. Gregor, <title>Notes on the Folklore of the North-East of
				Scotland</title> （London, 1881）, p. 127</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 183</bibl>. The full expression is reported
		by the Scholiast on <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 1.108"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 1.108</bibl>, <foreign
			lang="greek">ou)de\ h( *)/artemis ou(/tws a)\n e)to/ceuse</foreign>, “Not even Artemis
		could have shot like that.” The elliptical phrase is wrongly interpreted by the Sabbaitic
		scribe. See the Critical Note.</note>
	<note>This account of the attempted sacrifice of Iphigenia at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Aulis"
			key="perseus,Aulis">Aulis</placeName> and the substitution of a doe agrees with the
		narrative of the same events in the epic <title>Cypria</title> as summarized by Proclus （<bibl
			default="NO">Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 19</bibl>）. It is also in
		harmony with the tragedy of Euripides on the same subject. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. IA 87"
			valid="yes">Eur. IA 87ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. IA 358"
			valid="yes">Eur. IA 358ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. IA 1541"
			valid="yes">Eur. IA 1541ff.</bibl> Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 183</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. 1.108</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 98</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Ov. Met. 12.24"
			valid="yes">Ov. Met. 12.24-38</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis i.19-22</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. pp. 6ff., 141 (First
			Vatican Mythographer 20; Second Vatican Mythographer 202)</bibl>. Some said that
		Iphigenia was turned by the goddess into a bear or a bull (<bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 183</bibl>). Dictys Cretensis dispenses
		with the intervention of Artemis to save Iphigenia; according to him it was Achilles who
		rescued the maiden from the altar and conveyed her away to the Scythian king.</note>
	<note>The following story of Tenes, his stepmother's calumny, his banishment, and his elevation
		to the throne of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Tenedos"
			key="perseus,Tenedos">Tenedos</placeName>, is similarly told by <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.14.2"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.14.2-4</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 232</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. 1.38</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Il. i.38, p. 33</bibl>. Eustathius and the Scholiast on
		Homer call Tenes's sister Leucothea, and give Polyboea as an alternative name of their
		stepmother. According to Pausanias, the first wife of Cycnus was a daughter of Clytius, not
		of Laomedon. As to the names, Tzetzes agrees with Apollodorus, whom he probably copied. A
		rationalized version of the story is told by <bibl
			default="NO">Diod. 5.83</bibl>. According to him, Tenes was worshipped after his death
		as a god by the people of Tenedos, who made a precinct for him and offered sacrifices to him
		down to late times. No flute-player was allowed to enter the precinct, because a
		flute-player had borne false witness against Tenes; and the name of Achilles might not be
		mentioned within it, because Achilles had killed Tenes. Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Plut. Quaest. Graec. 28</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Plut. Quaest. Graec. 28</bibl>. Plutarch mentions the warning given by
		Thetis to Achilles not to kill Tenes, and says that the goddess specially charged one of
		Achilles's servants to remind her son of the warning. But in scouring the island Achilles
		fell in with the beautiful sister of Tenes and made love to her; Tenes defended his sister
		against her seducer, and in the brawl was slain by Achilles. When the slayer discovered whom
		he had slain, he killed the servant who ought to have warned him in time, and he buried
		Tenes on the spot where the sanctuary was afterwards dedicated to his worship. This version
		of the story clearly differs from the one followed by Apollodorus.</note>
	<note>This story of the exposure and desertion of Philoctetes in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7011173"
			key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName> appears to have been told in the epic
			<title>Cypria</title>, as we may judge by the brief summary of Proclus. See <bibl
			default="NO">Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 19</bibl>. According to
		Proclus, the Greeks were feasting in <placeName
			authname="perseus,Tenedos"
			key="perseus,Tenedos">Tenedos</placeName> when Philoctetes was bitten by a water-snake.
		This is not necessarily inconsistent with the statement of Apollodorus that the accident
		happened while the Greeks were sacrificing to Apollo, for the feast mentioned by Proclus may
		have been sacrificial. According to another version of the story, which Sophocles followed
		in his <title>Philoctetes</title>, the accident to Philoctetes happened, not in <placeName
			authname="perseus,Tenedos"
			key="perseus,Tenedos">Tenedos</placeName>, but in the small island of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Chryse"
			key="perseus,Chryse">Chryse</placeName>, where a goddess of that name was worshipped,
		and the serpent which bit Philoctetes was the guardian of her shrine. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Soph. Phil. 263"
			valid="yes">Soph. Phil. 263-270</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Soph. Phil. 1326"
			valid="yes">Soph. Phil. 1326-1328</bibl>. Later writers identified <placeName
			authname="perseus,Chryse"
			key="perseus,Chryse">Chryse</placeName> with Athena, and said that Philoctetes was stung
		while he was cleansing her altar or clearing it of the soil under which it was buried, as
		Tzetzes has it. See <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. ii.722</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 911</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Il. ii.724, p. 330</bibl>. But this identification is
		not supported by Sophocles nor by the evidence of a vase painting, which represents the
		shrine of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Chryse"
			key="perseus,Chryse">Chryse</placeName> with her name attached to her image. See <bibl
			default="NO">Jebb's Soph. Ph., p. xxxviii, section 21.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Baumeister, <title>Denkmäler des klassischen Altertums</title>, iii.1326,
			fig. 1325</bibl>. The island of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Chryse"
			key="perseus,Chryse">Chryse</placeName> is no doubt the “desert island near <placeName
			authname="tgn,7011173"
			key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName>” in which down to the first century B.C. were to be
		seen “an altar of Philoctetes, a bronze serpent, a bow, and a breastplate bound with
		fillets, the memorial of his sufferings” （<bibl
			default="NO">Appian, Mithridat. 77</bibl>）. The island had sunk in the sea before the
		time of Pausanias in the second century of our era （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 8.33.4"
			valid="yes">Paus. 8.33.4</bibl>）. According to a different account, the unfortunate
		encounter of Philoctetes with the snake took place in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7011173"
			key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName> itself, the island where he was abandoned by his
		comrades. See <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. ii.724, p. 330</bibl> and <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Il. ii.724, p. 330</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Soph. Ph. 270</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 102</bibl>. Philoctetes was commonly supposed to have
		received the bow and arrows of Hercules from that hero as a reward for his service in
		kindling the pyre on Mount Oeta. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Soph. Phil. 801"
			valid="yes">Soph. Phil. 801-803</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Diod. 4.38.4</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. ii.724</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 102</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Ov. Met. 9.229"
			valid="yes">Ov. Met. 9.229-234</bibl>. According to one account, which Servius has
		preserved, it was from these arrows, envenomed with the poison of the hydra, and not from a
		serpent, that Philoctetes received his grievous hurt. It is said that Hercules on the pyre
		solemnly charged his friend never to reveal the spot where his ashes should repose.
		Philoctetes promised with an oath to observe the wish of his dying friend, but afterwards he
		betrayed the secret by stamping with his foot on the grave. Hence on his way to the war one
		of the poisoned arrows fell upon and wounded the traitor foot. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 3.402"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 3.402</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. pp. 21, 132 (First Vatican
			Mythographer 59; Second Vatican Mythographer 165)</bibl>. Homer speaks of Philoctetes
		marooned by the Greeks in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7011173"
			key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName> and suffering agonies from the bite of the deadly
		water-snake （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 2.721"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.721-725</bibl>）, but he does not say how or where the sufferer
		was bitten. Sophocles represents <placeName
			authname="tgn,7011173"
			key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName> as a desert island （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Soph. Phil. 1"
			valid="yes">Soph. Phil. 1ff.</bibl>）. The fate of the forlorn hero, the ancient Robinson
		Crusoe, dwelling for ten years in utter solitude on his lonely isle, was a favourite theme
		of tragedy. Aeschylus, Sophocles, and Euripides all composed plays on the subject under the
		title of <title>Philoctetes</title>. See <bibl
			default="NO">Dio Chrysostom lii</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Jebb's Introduction to Soph. Ph., pp. xiiiff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">TGF (Nauck 2nd ed.), pp. 79ff., 613ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>As to the embassy of Ulysses and Menelaus to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> to demand the surrender of Helen, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 3.205"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 3.205ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 11.138"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 11.138ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 19</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Bacchyl. Dith. 15.1"
			valid="yes">Bacch. 14(15), ed. Jebb</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hdt. 2.118"
			valid="yes">Hdt. 2.118</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Antehomerica 154ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. iii.206</bibl>. According to the author of the epic
			<title>Cypria</title>, as reported by <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 19</bibl>, the
		embassy was sent before the first battle, in which Protesilaus fell （see below）; according
		to Tzetzes, it was sent before the Greek army assembled at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Aulis"
			key="perseus,Aulis">Aulis</placeName>; according to the <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. iii.206</bibl>, it was despatched from <placeName
			authname="perseus,Tenedos"
			key="perseus,Tenedos">Tenedos</placeName>. Herodotus says that the envoys were sent
		after the landing of the army in the <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002331"
			key="tgn,7002331">Troad</placeName>. Sophocles wrote a play on the subject of the
		embassy, called <title>The Demand for the Surrender of Helen</title>. See <bibl
			default="NO">TGF (Nauck 2nd ed.), pp. 171ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, vol. i. pp.
			121ff.</bibl> Libanius has bequeathed to us two imaginary speeches, which are supposed
		to have been delivered by the Greek ambassadors, Menelaus and Ulysses, to the Trojan
		assembly before the opening of hostilities, while the Greek army was encamped within sight
		of the walls of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. See <bibl
			default="NO">Libanius, Declam. iii. and iv. （vol. v. pp. 199ff., ed. R.
		Foerster）</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 2.698"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.698-702</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 19</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 245</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Chiliades ii.759ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Antehomerica 221ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Il. ii.701, p. 325, and on Od. xi.521, p. 1697</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 4.2.5"
			valid="yes">Paus. 4.2.5</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 103</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis ii.11</bibl>. The common tradition, followed by
		Apollodorus, was that Protesilaus fell by the hand of Hector; but according to others, his
		slayer was Aeneas, or Achates, or Euphorbus. See <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Il. ii.701, p. 325, and on Od. xi.521, p. 1697</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Antehomerica 230ff.</bibl> The Greeks had received an oracle that
		the first of their number to leap from the ships would be the first to perish. See <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 245</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 113</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Ovid, Her. xiii.93ff.</bibl> Protesilaus was reckoned by <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 1.34.2"
			valid="yes">Paus. 1.34.2</bibl> among the men who after death received divine honours
		from the Greeks. He was buried in the Thracian Chersonese, opposite the <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002331"
			key="tgn,7002331">Troad</placeName>, and was there worshipped as a god （<bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 532</bibl>）. His grave at Elaeus, or Eleus,
		in the peninsula was enclosed in a sacred precinct, and his worshippers testified their
		devotion by dedicating to him many vessels of gold and silver and bronze, together with
		raiment and other offerings; but when Xerxes invaded <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000074"
			key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, these treasures were carried off by the Persians,
		who desecrated the holy ground by sowing it with corn and turning cattle loose on it to
		graze （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hdt. 9.116"
			valid="yes">Hdt. 9.116</bibl>）. Tall elms grew within the sacred precinct and
		overshadowed the grave; and it is said that the leaves of the trees that looked across the
		narrow sea to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, where Protesilaus perished, burgeoned early but
		soon faded and fell, like the hero himself, while the trees that looked away from <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> still kept their foliage fresh and fair. See <bibl
			default="NO">Philostratus, Her. iii.1</bibl>. Others said that when the elms had shot up
		so high that <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> could be seen from them away across the water, the
		topmost boughs immediately withered. See <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica vii.408ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Pliny, Nat. Hist. xvi.238</bibl>.</note>
	<note>According to the author of the epic <title>Cypria</title> the name of Protesilaus's wife
		was Polydora, daughter of Meleager （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 4.2.7"
			valid="yes">Paus. 4.2.7</bibl>）. Later writers, like Apollodorus, called her Laodamia.
		As to her tragic tale, see <bibl
			default="NO">Lucian, Dial. Mort. xxiii.</bibl> （who does not name her）; <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Il. ii.701, p. 325</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Aristides, vol. iii. pp. 671ff., ed. Dindorf</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Chiliades ii.763ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Prop. 1.19"
			valid="yes">Prop. i.19.7-10</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 103, 104</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Ovid, Her. xiii</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 6.447"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 6.447</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. pp. 51, 147 (First Vatican
			Mythographer 158; Second Vatican Mythographer 215)</bibl>. According to <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 103</bibl>, Laodamia had prayed that Protesilaus might be
		restored to her for only three hours; her prayer was granted, but she could not bear the
		grief of parting with him, and died in his arms （<bibl
			default="NO">Servius, l.c.</bibl>）. A rationalistic version of the story ran that
		Laodamia had made a waxen image of her dead husband and secretly embraced it, till her
		father ordered it to be burned, when she threw herself into the fire and perished with the
		image （<bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 104</bibl>）. According to Ovid, Laodamia made the waxen image
		of her absent lord and fondled it even in his lifetime. Her sad story was the theme of a
		tragedy of Euripides （<bibl
			default="NO">TGF (Nauck 2nd ed.), pp. 563ff.</bibl>）, as it is of a well-known poem of
		Wordsworth （Laodameia）.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 19</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Pind. O. 2"
			valid="yes">Pind. O. 2.82(147)</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aristot. Rh. 2.22.10"
			valid="yes">Aristot. Rh. 2.1396b 16-18</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica iv.468ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Antehomerica 257ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Theocritus xvi.49</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Ov. Met. 12.70-140</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis ii.12</bibl>. Cycnus was said to be invulnerable （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aristot. Rh. 2.22.10"
			valid="yes">Aristot. Rh. 2.1396b 16-18</bibl>）: hence neither the spear nor the sword of
		Achilles could make any impression on his body, and the hero was reduced to the necessity of
		throttling him with the thongs of his own helmet. So Ovid tells the tale, adding that the
		seagod, his father Poseidon, changed the dead Cycnus into a swan, whose name （Cygnus, <foreign
			lang="greek">ku/knos</foreign>） he had borne in life.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 20</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. xxiv.257</bibl> （where for <foreign
			lang="greek">o)xeuqh=nai</foreign> it has been proposed to read <foreign
			lang="greek">loxhqh=nai</foreign> or <foreign
			lang="greek">logxeuqh=nai）;</foreign>
		<bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Il. xxiv.251,p. 1348</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dio Chrysostom xi. vol. i. p. 189, ed. L. Dindorf</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 307-313</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Verg. A. 1.474"
			valid="yes">Verg. A. 1.474ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 1.474"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 1.474</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. p. 66 (First Vatican
			Mythographer 210)</bibl>. Troilus is represented as a youth, but the stories concerning
		his death are various. According to Eustathius, the lad was exercising his horses in the
		Thymbraeum or sanctuary of the Thymbraean Apollo, when Achilles killed him with his spear.
		Tzetzes says that he was a son of Hecuba by Apollo, though nominally by Priam, that he fled
		from his assailant to the temple of Apollo, and was cut down by Achilles at the altar. There
		was a prophecy that <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> could not be taken if Troilus should live to the age
		of twenty （so the First Vatican Mythographer）. This may have been the motive of Achilles for
		slaying the lad. According to <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis iv.9</bibl>, Troilus was taken prisoner and publicly
		slaughtered in cold blood by order of Achilles. The indefatigable Sophocles, as usual, wrote
		a tragedy on the subject. See <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, vol. ii. pp.
			253ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 11.34"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 11.34ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 13.746"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 13.746ff.</bibl> Lycaon was captured by Achilles when he was
		cutting sticks in the orchard of his father Priam. After being sold by his captor into
		slavery in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7011173"
			key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName> he was ransomed and returned to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, but meeting Achilles in battle a few days later, he
		was ruthlessly slain by him. The story seems to have been told also in the epic
			<title>Cypria</title>. See <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p.
		20</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 20.90"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 20.90ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 20.188"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 20.188ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p.
		20</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 9.129"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 9.129</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis ii.16</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 2.691"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.691</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 6.397"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 6.397</bibl>.</note>
	<note>It was at the sack of Lyrnessus that Achilles captured his concubine Briseis after slaying
		her husband. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 2.688"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.688ff.</bibl>, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 19.60"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 19.60</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 19.291"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 19. 291ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 20.92"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 20.92</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 20.191"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 20.191ff.</bibl> Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis ii.17</bibl>.</note>
	<note>With the following list of the Trojans and their allies, compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 2.816"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.816-877</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 2.842"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.842ff.</bibl>, where the poet describes Hippothous as the son of
		the Pelasgian Lethus. Apollodorus, misunderstanding the passage, has converted the adjective
		Pelasgian into a noun Pelasgus.</note>
	<note>Homer calls him Chromis （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 2.858"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.858</bibl>）.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 1.1"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 1.1ff.</bibl> From this point Apollodorus follows the incidents of
		the Trojan war as related by Homer.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 3.15"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 3.15-382</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 4.85"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 4.85ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 5.1"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 5.1-417</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 6.119"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 6.119-236</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 7.66"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 7.66-312</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 7.436"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 7.436-441</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 8.53"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 8.53-565</bibl>.</note>
	<note>The embassy of Ulysses, Phoenix, and Ajax to Achilles is the subject of the ninth book of
		the <title>Iliad</title>. <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 9"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 9</bibl>. Libanius composed an imaginary reply to the speech of
		Ulysses （<bibl
			default="NO">Libanius, Declam. v., vol. v. pp. 303-360, ed. R. Foerster</bibl>）.</note>
	<note>These events are narrated in the tenth book of the <title> Iliad </title>. <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 10"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 10</bibl>. They form the subject of Euripides's tragedy
			<title>Rhesus</title>, the only extant Greek drama of which the plot is derived from the
		action of the <title> Iliad </title>.</note>
	<note>These events are told in the eleventh book of the <title> Iliad </title>, (<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 11"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 11</bibl>).</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 12.436"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 12.436ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 15.716"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 15.716ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>These events are narrated in the sixteenth book of the <title> Iliad </title>, (<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 16"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 16</bibl>).</note>
	<note>These events are the subject of the seventeenth book of the <title> Iliad </title>, (<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 17"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 17</bibl>).</note>
	<note>These events are narrated in the eighteenth (<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 18"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 18</bibl>) and nineteenth (<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 19"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 19</bibl>) books of the <title> Iliad </title>.</note>
	<note>These events are related in the twentieth (<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 20"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 20</bibl>) and twenty-first (<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 21"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 21</bibl>) books of the <title> Iliad </title>. As to the slaying
		of Asteropaeus by Achilles, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 21.139"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 21.139-204</bibl>. As to the combat of Achilles with the river
		Scamander, and the drying up of the streams of the river by the fire-god Hephaestus, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 21.211"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 21.211-382</bibl>. The whole passage affords a striking example of
		the way in which the Greeks conceived rivers as personal beings, endowed with human shape,
		human voice, and human passions. Incidentally （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 21.130"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 21.130-132</bibl>） we hear of sacrifices of bulls and horses to a
		river, the horses being thrown alive into the stream.</note>
	<note>The combat of Achilles with Hector, and the death of Hector, form the subject of the
		twenty-second book of the <title> Iliad </title>, (<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 22"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 22</bibl>).</note>
	<note>The burial of Patroclus and the funeral games celebrated in his honour, are described in
		the twenty-third book of the <title> Iliad </title>, (<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 23"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 23</bibl>).</note>
	<note>These events are narrated in the twenty-fourth book of the <title> Iliad </title>, (<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 24"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 24</bibl>).</note>
	<note>These events were narrated in the <title>Aethiopis</title> of Arctinus, as we learn from
		the summary of that poem drawn up by Proclus. See <bibl
			default="NO">Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 33</bibl>. Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Diod. 2.46.5</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica i.18ff., 227ff., 538ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 6ff., 100ff., 136ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 999</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis iv.2ff.</bibl> Quintus Smyrnaeus explains more fully than
		Apollodorus the reason why Penthesilia came to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> （<bibl
			default="NO">Posthomerica i.18ff.</bibl>）. Aiming at a deer in the chase, she had
		accidentally killed her sister Hippolyte with her spear, and, haunted by the Furies of the
		slain woman, she came to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> to be purified from her guilt. The same story is
		told more briefly by Diodorus Siculus. According to <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 999</bibl>, Thersites excited the wrath of
		Achilles, not only by his foul accusations, but by gouging out the eyes of the beautiful
		Amazon. In the <title>Aethiopis</title> it was related how, after killing the base churl,
		Achilles sailed to <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002672"
			key="tgn,7002672">Lesbos</placeName> and was there purified from the guilt of murder by
		Ulysses, but not until he had offered sacrifice to Apollo, Artemis, and Latona. See <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 33</bibl>. The
		mother of Penthesilia is named Otrere （Otrera） by <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 997</bibl> and <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 112</bibl>, in agreement with Apollodorus. Machaon is usually
		said to have been killed by Eurypylus, and not, as Apollodorus says, by Penthesilia. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 3.26.9"
			valid="yes">Paus. 3.26.9</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica vi.390ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 520ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 113</bibl>. From <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 3.26.9"
			valid="yes">Paus. 3.26.9</bibl> we learn that Eurypylus, not Penthesilia, was
		represented as the slayer in the <title>Little Iliad</title> of Lesches.</note>
	<note>See above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. Epit. E.1.17"
			valid="yes">Apollod. E.1.17</bibl>. The two passages are practically duplicates of each
		other. The former occurs in the Sabbaitic, the latter in the Vatican <title>Epitome</title>
		of Apollodorus. The author of the one compendium preferred to relate the incident in the
		history of Theseus, the other in the history of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.</note>
	<note>These events were narrated in the <title>Aethiopis</title> of Arctinus, as we learn from
		the summary of Proclus. See <bibl
			default="NO">Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 33</bibl>. Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica ii.100ff., 235ff., 452ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 234ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis iv.6</bibl>. The fight between Memnon and Achilles was
		represented on the throne of Apollo at Amyclae, and on the chest of Cypselus at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Olympia"
			key="perseus,Olympia">Olympia</placeName> （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 3.18.12"
			valid="yes">Paus. 3.18.12</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 5.19.1"
			valid="yes">Paus. 5.19.1</bibl>）. It was also the subject of a group of statuary, which
		was set up beside the Hippodamium at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Olympia"
			key="perseus,Olympia">Olympia</placeName> （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 5.22.2"
			valid="yes">Paus. 5.22.2</bibl>）. Some fragments of the pedestal which supported the
		group have been discovered: one of them bears the name MEMNON inscribed in archaic letters.
		See <bibl
			default="NO"><title>Die Inschriften von Olympia</title> 662</bibl>; and <bibl
			default="NO">Frazer, commentary on Pausanias, vol. iii. pp. 629ff.</bibl> Aeschylus
		wrote a tragedy on the subject called <title>Psychostasia</title>, in which he described
		Zeus weighing the souls of the rival heroes in scales. See <bibl
			default="NO">Plut. De audiendis poetis 2</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. viii.70</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">TGF (Nauck 2nd ed.), pp. 88ff.</bibl> A play of Sophocles, called
			<title>The Ethiopians</title>, probably dealt with the same theme. See <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, vol. i. pp.
			22ff.</bibl> The slaying of Antilochus by Memnon is mentioned by <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 4.187"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 4.187ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>The death of Achilles was similarly related in the <title>Aethiopis</title> of Arctinus.
		See <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, pp. 33ff.</bibl>
		Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica iii.26-387</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 107</bibl>. All these writers agree with Apollodorus in
		saying that the fatal wound was inflicted on the heel of Achilles. The story ran that at his
		birth his mother Thetis made Achilles invulnerable by dipping him in the water of Styx; but
		his heel, by which she held him, was not wetted by the water and so remained vulnerable. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 6.57"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 6.57</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Lactantius Placidus on Statius, Achill. i.134</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Lactantius Placidus, Narrat. Fabul. xii.6</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Fulgentius, Mytholog. iii.7</bibl>. Tradition varied as to the agent of
		Achilles's death. Some writers, like Arctinus and Apollodorus, say that the hero was killed
		by Apollo and Paris jointly. Thus in <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 22.359"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 22.359ff.</bibl>） the dying Hector prophesies that Achilles will be
		slain by Paris and Apollo at the Scaean gate; and the same prophecy is put by Homer more
		darkly into the mouth of the talking horse Xanthus, who, like Balaam's ass, warns his master
		of the danger that besets his path （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 19.404"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 19.404ff.</bibl>）. According to Virgil and Ovid, it was the hand of
		Paris that discharged the fatal arrow, but the hand of Apollo that directed it to the mark.
		See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Verg. A. 6.56"
			valid="yes">Verg. A. 6.56-58</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Ov. Met. 12.597"
			valid="yes">Ov. Met. 12.597-609</bibl>. According to Hyginus, it was Apollo in the guise
		of Paris who transfixed the mortal heel of Achilles with an arrow （<bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 107</bibl>）. But in one passage （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 21.277"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 21.277ff.</bibl>） homer speaks of the death of Achilles as wrought
		by the shafts of Apollo alone; and this version was followed by <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica iii.60ff.</bibl> and apparently by
		Aeschylus, Sophocles and Horace. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Plat. Rep. 2.383a"
			valid="yes">Plat. Rep. 2.383a-b</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Soph. Phil. 334"
			valid="yes">Soph. Phil. 334ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hor. Carm. 4.6.1"
			valid="yes">Hor. Carm. 4.6.1ff.</bibl> Other writers, on the contrary, speak of Paris
		alone as the slayer of Achilles. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Andr. 655"
			valid="yes">Eur. And. 655</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hec. 387"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hec. 387ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Plut. Quaest. Conviv. ix.13.2</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Plut. Lys. 4"
			valid="yes">Plut. Lys. 4</bibl>. A very different version of the story connected the
		death of Achilles with a romantic passion he had conceived for Polyxena, daughter of Priam.
		It is said that Priam offered her hand in marriage to Achilles on condition that the siege
		of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> was raised. In the negotiations which were carried
		on for this purpose Achilles went alone and unarmed to the temple of Thymbraean Apollo and
		was there treacherously assassinated, Deiphobus clasping him to his breast in a pretended
		embrace of friendship while Paris stabbed him with a sword. See <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 385-423</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Philostratus, Her. xx.16ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 110</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis iv.10ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 6.57"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 6.57</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Lactantius Placidus on Statius, Achill. i.134</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dares Phrygius, De excidio Trojae 34</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. pp. 13, 143 (First Vatican
			Mythographer 36; Second Vatican Mythographer 205)</bibl>. Of these writers, the Second
		Vatican Mythographer tells us that Achilles first saw Polyxena, Hector's sister, when she
		stood on a tower in the act of throwing down bracelets and earrings with which to ransom
		Hector's body, and that when Achilles came to the temple of the Thymbraean Apollo to ratify
		the treaty of marriage and peace, Paris lurked behind the image of the god and shot the
		confiding hero with an arrow. This seems to be the account of the death which <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 6.57"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 6.57</bibl> and <bibl
			default="NO">Lactantius Placidus on Statius, Achill. i.134</bibl> followed in their
		briefer narrative. Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Nonnus, in Westermann's Mythographi Graeci, Appendix Narrationum 62, p.
			382</bibl>.</note>
	<note>According to Arctinus in the <title>Aethiopis</title>, when the body of Achilles was lying
		in state, his mother Thetis came with the Muses and her sisters and mourned over her dead
		son; then she snatched it away from the pyre and conveyed it to the White Isle; but the
		Greeks raised a sepulchral mound and held games in honour of the departed hero. See <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 34</bibl>.
		Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 24.43"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 24.43-92</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica iii.525-787</bibl> （the laying-out of the
		body, the lamentation of Thetis, the Nereids, and the Muses, and the burning of the corpse）; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 431-467</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis iv.13, 15</bibl>. Homer tells how the bones of Achilles,
		after his body had been burnt on the pyre, were laid with the bones of his friend Patroclus
		in a golden urn, made by Hephaestus, which Thetis had received from Dionysus. The urn was
		buried at the headland of Sigeum, according to Tzetzes and Dictys Cretensis. In <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, iii.766-780</bibl> we read how Poseidon comforted Thetis
		by assuring her that Achilles, her sorrow, was not dead, for he himself would bestow on the
		departed hero an island in the Euxine Sea where he should be a god for evermore, worshipped
		with sacrifices by the neighbouring tribes. The promised land was the White Isle mentioned
		by Apollodorus. It is described as a wooded island off the mouth of the Danube. In it there
		was a temple of Achilles with an image of him; and there the hero was said to dwell immortal
		with Helen for his wife and his friends Patroclus and Antilochus for his companions. There
		he chanted the verses of Homer, and mariners who sailed near the island could hear the song
		wafted clearly across the water; while such as put in to the shore or anchored off the
		coast, heard the trampling of horses, the shouts of warriors, and the clash of arms. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 3.19.11"
			valid="yes">Paus. 3.19.11-13</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Philostratus, Her. xx.32-40</bibl>. As the mortal remains of Achilles were
		buried in the <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002331"
			key="tgn,7002331">Troad</placeName>, and only his immortal spirit was said to dwell in
		the White Isle, the statement of Apollodorus that the Greeks interred him in the White Isle
		must be regarded as erroneous, whether the error is due to Apollodorus himself, or, as is
		more probable, either to his abbreviator or to a copyist. Perhaps in the original form of
		his work Apollodorus followed Arctinus in describing how Thetis snatched the body of
		Achilles from the pyre and transported it to the White Isle.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Ap. Rhod., Argon. iv.810ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 174</bibl>. According to the <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Ap. Rhod., Argon. iv.815</bibl>, the first to affirm that
		Achilles married Medea in the Elysian Fields was the poet Ibycus, and the tale was
		afterwards repeated by Simonides. The story is unknown to Homer, who describes the shade of
		Achilles repining at his lot and striding alone in the Asphodel Meadow （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 11.471"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11.471-540</bibl>）.</note>
	<note>The funeral games in honour of Achilles are described at full length, in the orthodox
		manner, by <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica iv.88-595</bibl>. He agrees with
		Apollodorus in representing Teucer and Ajax as victorious in the contests of archery and
		quoit-throwing respectively （<bibl
			default="NO">Posthomerica iv.405ff., 436ff.</bibl>）; and he seems to have described
		Eumelus as the winner of the chariot-race （<bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica iv.500ff.</bibl>）, but the conclusion of
		the race is lost through a gap in the text.</note>
	<note>These events were narrated in the <title>Little Iliad</title> of Lesches. See <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 36</bibl>;
		compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aristot. Poet. 1459b.4"
			valid="yes">Aristot. Poet. 1459b 4ff.</bibl>. The contest between Ajax and Ulysses for
		the arms of Achilles was also related in the <title>Aethiopis</title> of Arctinus. See <bibl
			default="NO">Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 34</bibl>. It was known to <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 11.542"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11.542ff.</bibl>, who tells us that the Trojans and Pallas Athena
		acted as judges and awarded the arms to Ulysses. A <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Od. 11.547</bibl> informs us that Agamemnon, unwilling to
		undertake the invidious duty of deciding between the two competitors, referred the dispute
		to the decision of the Trojan prisoners, inquiring of them which of the two heroes had done
		most harm to the Trojans. The prisoners decided that Ulysses was the man, and the arms were
		therefore awarded to him. According to another account, which was adopted by the author of
		the <title>Little Iliad</title>, the Greeks on the advice of Nestor sent spies to the walls
		of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> to overhear the Trojans discussing the respective
		merits of the two champions. They heard two girls debating the question, and thinking that
		she who gave the preference to Ulysses reasoned the better, they decided accordingly. See <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Aristoph. Kn. 1056</bibl>. According to <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Pind. N. 8"
			valid="yes">Pind. N. 8.26(45)ff.</bibl>, it was the Greeks who by secret votes decided
		in favour of Ulysses. The subject was treated by Aeschylus in a lost play called <title>The
			Decision of the Arms</title>. See <bibl
			default="NO">TGF (Nauck 2nd ed.), pp. 57ff.</bibl> The madness and suicide of Ajax,
		consequent on his disappointment at not being awarded the arms, are the theme of Sophocles's
		extant tragedy <title>Ajax</title>. As to the contest for the arms, see further <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica v.121ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 481ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Zenobius, Cent. i.43</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 107</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Ov. Met. 12.620"
			valid="yes">Ov. Met. 12.620-628</bibl>, xiii.1-398. Quintus Smyrnaeus and Tzetzes agree
		in representing the Trojan captives as the judges in the dispute, while Ovid speaks of the
		Greek chiefs sitting in judgment and deciding in favour of Ulysses. According to <bibl
			default="NO">Zenobius, Cent. i.43</bibl>, Ajax in his frenzy scourged two rams,
		believing that he was scourging Agamemnon and Menelaus. This account is based on the
		description of the frenzy of Ajax in <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Soph. Aj. 97"
			valid="yes">Soph. Aj. 97-110</bibl>, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Soph. Aj. 237"
			valid="yes">Soph. Aj. 237-244</bibl>）.</note>
	<note>Similarly the author of the <title>Little Iliad</title> said that the body of Ajax was not
		burned, but placed in a coffin “on account of the wrath of the king.” See <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Il. ii.557, p. 285</bibl>. Philostratus tells us that
		the body was laid in the earth by direction of the seer Calchas, “because suicides may not
		lawfully receive the burial by fire” （<bibl
			default="NO">Philostratus, Her. xiii.7</bibl>）. This was probably the true reason for
		the tradition that the corpse was not cremated in the usual way. For the ghosts of suicides
		appear to be commonly dreaded; hence unusual modes of disposing of their bodies are adopted
		in order to render their spirits powerless for mischief. For example, the Baganda of Central
		Africa, who commonly bury their dead in the earth, burn the bodies of suicides on waste land
		or at crossroads in order to destroy the ghosts; for they believe that if the ghost of a
		suicide is not thus destroyed, it will tempt other people to imitate its example. As an
		additional precaution everyone who passed the place where the body of a suicide had been
		burnt threw some grass or a few sticks on the spot, “so as to prevent the ghost from
		catching him, in case it had not been destroyed.” For the same reason, if a man took his
		life by hanging himself on a tree, the tree was torn up by the roots and burned with the
		body; if he had killed himself in a house, the house was pulled down and the materials
		consumed with fire; for “people feared to live in a house in which a suicide had taken
		place, lest they too should be tempted to commit the same crime.” See <bibl
			default="NO">J. Roscoe, <title>The Baganda</title> （London, 1911）, pp. 20ff.,
		289</bibl>. Similar customs prevailed among the Banyoro, a neighbouring nation of Central
		Africa. “It was said to be necessary to destroy a tree upon which a person had hanged
		himself and to burn down a house in which a person had committed suicide, otherwise they
		would be a danger to people in general and would influence them to commit suicide.” See <bibl
			default="NO">J. Roscoe, <title>The Northern Bantu</title> （Cambridge, 1915）, pp.
			24ff.</bibl> （where, however, the burning of the body is not expressly mentioned）. In
		like manner the Hos of <placeName
			authname="tgn,7016577"
			key="tgn,7016577">Togoland</placeName>, in West Africa, are much afraid of the ghost of
		a suicide. They believe that the ghost of a man who has hanged himself will torment the
		first person who sees the body. Hence when the relations of such a man approach the corpse
		they protect themselves against the ghost by wearing magical cords and smearing their faces
		with a magical powder. The tree on which a man hanged himself is cut down, and the branch on
		which he tied the fatal noose is lopped off. To this branch the corpse is then tied and
		dragged ruthlessly through the woods, over stones and through thorny bushes, to the place
		where “men of blood,” that is, all who die a violent death, are buried. There they dig a
		shallow grave in great haste and throw the body in. Having done so they run home; for they
		say that the ghosts of “men of blood” fling stones at such as do not retreat fast enough,
		and that he who is struck by one of these stones must die. The houses of such men are broken
		down and burnt. A suicide is believed to defile the land and to prevent rain from falling.
		Hence the district where a man has killed himself must be purified by a sacrifice offered to
		the Earth-god. See <bibl
			default="NO">J. Spieth, <title>Die Ewe-Stämme</title> （Berlin, 1906）, pp. 272, 274,
			276ff. 756, 758</bibl>. As to the special treatment of the bodies of suicides, see <bibl
			default="NO">R. Lasch, “Die Behandlung der Leiche des Selbstmorders,”
				<title>Globus</title>, lxxvi. （Brunswick, 1899, pp. 63-66）</bibl>. In the
			<title>Ajax</title> of Sophocles the rites of burial are at first refused, but
		afterwards conceded, to the dead body of Ajax; and though these ceremonies are not
		described, we may assume that they included the burning of the corpse on a pyre. This
		variation from what appears to be the usual tradition may have been introduced by Sophocles
		out of deference to the religious feelings of the Athenians, who worshipped Ajax as a hero,
		and who would have been shocked to think of his remains being denied the ordinary funeral
		honours. See <bibl
			default="NO">Jebb's Introduction to his edition of the Ajax（Cambridge, 1896）, pp.
			xxix.ff.</bibl> As to the worship of Ajax at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Athens"
			key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 1.35.3"
			valid="yes">Paus. 1.35.3</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Corpus Inscriptionum Atticarum ii. 467-471</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dittenberger, Sylloge Inscriptionum Graecarum 717, vol. ii. p. 370</bibl>.
		From these inscriptions we learn that the Athenian youths used to sail across every year to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Salamis, Cyprus"
			key="perseus,Salamis, Cyprus">Salamis</placeName> and there sacrifice to Ajax.</note>
	<note>These events are related in precisely the same way, though with many poetic
		embellishments, by <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica ix.325-479</bibl> （the fetching of
		Philoctetes from <placeName
			authname="tgn,7011173"
			key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName> and the healing of him by Podalirius）, <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica x.206ff.</bibl> （Paris wounded to death by
		the arrows of Philoctetes）. The story was told somewhat differently by Lesches in the
			<title>Little Iliad</title>. According to him, the prophecy that <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> could not be taken without the help of Philoctetes
		was uttered, not by Calchas, but by the Trojan seer Helenus, whom Ulysses had captured;
		Philoctetes was brought from <placeName
			authname="tgn,7011173"
			key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName> by Diomedes alone, and he was healed, not by
		Podalirius, but by Machaon. The account of <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 571-595</bibl> agrees with that of Lesches in respect
		of the prophecy of Helenus and the cure by Machaon. Sophocles also followed the
			<title>Little Iliad</title> in putting the prophecy in the mouth of the captured Trojan
		seer Helenus （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Soph. Phil. 604"
			valid="yes">Soph. Phil. 604-613</bibl>）. Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 911</bibl>. In their plays on the subject
		（see above, note on <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. Epit. E.3.27"
			valid="yes">Apollod. E.3.27</bibl>） Euripides and Sophocles differed as to the envoys
		whom the Greeks sent to bring the wounded Philoctetes from <placeName
			authname="tgn,7011173"
			key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName> to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. According to Euripides, with whom Apollodorus,
		Quintus Smyrnaeus, and <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 103</bibl> agree, the envoys were Ulysses and Diomedes;
		according to Sophocles, they were Ulysses and Neoptolemus, son of Achilles. See <bibl
			default="NO">Dio Chrysostom lii. vol. ii. p. 161, ed. L. Dindorf</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Jebb's Introduction to his edition of Sophocles, Philoctetes （Cambridge,
			1898）, pp. xvff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">TGF (Nauck 2nd ed.), pp. 613ff.</bibl> However, while Sophocles diverges
		from what seems to have been the usual story by representing Neoptolemus instead of Diomedes
		as the companion of Ulysses on this errand, he implicitly recognizes the other version by
		putting it in the mouth of the merchant （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Soph. Phil. 570"
			valid="yes">Soph. Phil. 570-597</bibl>）. A painting at the entrance to the acropolis of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Athens"
			key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> represented Ulysses or Diomedes （it is uncertain
		which） in the act of carrying off the bow of Philoctetes. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 1.22.6"
			valid="yes">Paus. 1.22.6</bibl>, with <bibl
			default="NO">Frazer's commentary (vol. ii. pp. 263ff.)</bibl>. The combat between
		Philoctetes and Paris is described by <bibl
			default="NO">Malalas, Chr. v. pp. 110ff., ed. L. Dindorf</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Conon 34</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 2.166"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 2.166</bibl>. The marriage of Deiphobus to Helen after the
		death of Paris was related in the <title>Little Iliad</title>. See <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 36</bibl>.
		Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 600ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on. Lycophron, 143, 168</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Tro. 959"
			valid="yes">Eur. Tro. 959ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. 24.251, and on Od. iv.276</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis iv.22</bibl>. The marriage was seemingly known to <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 4.276"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 4.276</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the capture of Helenus and his prophecy, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Soph. Phil. 604"
			valid="yes">Soph. Phil. 604ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Soph. Phil. 1337"
			valid="yes">Soph. Phil. 1337ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"> Conon 34</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 571-579</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Chiliades vi.508-515</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 2.166"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 2.166</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis ii.18</bibl>. The mode of his capture and the substance of
		his prophecies were variously related. The need of fetching the bones of Pelops is mentioned
		by Tzetzes among the predictions of Helenus; and the necessity of obtaining the Palladium is
		recorded by Conon and Servius. According to <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 5.13.4"
			valid="yes">Paus. 5.13.4</bibl>, it was a shoulder-blade of Pelops that was brought from <placeName
			authname="perseus,Pisa"
			key="perseus,Pisa">Pisa</placeName> to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>; on the return from <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> the bone was lost in a shipwreck, but afterwards
		recovered by a fisherman.</note>
	<note>As to the Palladium, see above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. 3.12.3"
			valid="yes">Apollod. 3.12.3</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the fetching of Neoptolemus from Scyros, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 11.506"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11.506ff.</bibl>; the <bibl
			default="NO">Little Iliad of Lesches, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum
			Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, pp. 36ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Pind. Pa. 6.98ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Soph. Phil. 343"
			valid="yes">Soph. Phil. 343-356</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Philostratus Junior, Im. 2</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica vi.57-113, vii.169- 430</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 523-534</bibl>. Apollodorus agrees with Sophocles in
		saying that the Greek envoys who fetched Neoptolemus from Scyros were Ulysses and Phoenix.
		According to Quintus Smyrnaeus, they were Ulysses and Diomedes. Ulysses is the only envoy
		mentioned by Homer, Lesches, and Tzetzes; and Phoenix is the only envoy mentioned by
		Philostratus. Pindar speaks vaguely of “messengers.” In this passage I have adopted Wagner's
		conjecture <foreign
			lang="greek">pei/qousi &lt; au)&gt; to\n Neopto/lemon proe/sqai</foreign>, “persuaded
		him to let Neoptolemus go.” If this conjecture is not accepted, we seem forced to translate
		the passage “persuaded Neoptolemus to venture.” But I cannot cite any exact parallel to such
		a use of the middle of <foreign
			lang="greek">proi/+hmi.</foreign> When employed absolutely, the verb seems often to
		convey a bad meaning. Thus Demosthenes uses it in the sense of “throwing away a chance,”
		“neglecting an opportunity” （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Dem. 19.150"
			valid="yes">Dem.19.150, 152</bibl>, <foreign
			lang="greek">mh\ pro/esqai, ou) proh/sesqai</foreign>）. Iphicrates employed it with the
		same significance （quoted by <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aristot. Rh. 2.23.3"
			valid="yes">Aristot. Rh. 2.1397b</bibl>
		<foreign
			lang="greek">dio/ti proei=to</foreign>）. Aristotle applied the verb to a man who had
		“thrown away” his health （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aristot. Nic. Eth. 1114a"
			valid="yes">Aristot. Nic. Eth. 3.1114a 15</bibl>, <foreign
			lang="greek">to/te me\n ou)=n e)ch=n au)tw=| mh\ nosei=n, proeme/nw| d' ou)ke/ti,
			w(/sper ou)d' a)fe/nti li/qon e)/t' au)to\n dunato\n a)nalabei=n</foreign>）. However,
		elsewhere Aristotle uses the word to describe the lavish liberality of generous men （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aristot. Rh. 1.9.5"
			valid="yes">Aristot. Rh. 1.1366b</bibl>, <foreign
			lang="greek">ei)=ta h( e)leuqerio/ths: proi/+entai ga\r kai\ ou)k a)ntagwni/zontai peri\
			tw=n xrhma/twn, w(=n ma/lista e)fi/entai a)/lloi</foreign>）. In the present passage of
		Apollodorus, if Wagner's emendation is not accepted, we might perhaps read <foreign
			lang="greek">&lt;mh\&gt;pro/esqai</foreign> and translate, “persuaded Neoptolemus not to
		throw away the chance.” But it is better to acquiesce in Wagner's simple and probable
		correction.</note>
	<note>As to the single combat of Eurypylus and Neoptolemus, and the death of Eurypylus, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 11.516"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11.516-521</bibl>; the <bibl
			default="NO">Little Iliad of Lesches, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum
			Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 37</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica viii.128-220</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 560-565</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis iv.17</bibl>. Eurypulus was king of <placeName
			authname="tgn,7016748"
			key="tgn,7016748">Mysia</placeName>. At first his mother Astyoche refused to let him go
		to the Trojan war, but Priam overcame her scruples by the present of a golden vine. See <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Od. xi.520</bibl>. The brief account which Apollodorus
		gives of the death of Eurypylus agrees closely with the equally summary narrative of
		Proclus. Sophocles composed a tragedy on the subject, of which some very mutilated fragments
		have been discovered in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7016833"
			key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>. See <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, vol. i. pp.
			146ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">A. S. Hunt, <title>Tragicorum Graecorum Fragmenta Papyracea nuper
				reperta</title> （Oxford; no date, no pagination）</bibl>.</note>
	<note>These events were narrated in the <title>Little Iliad</title> of Lesches, as we learn from
		the summary of <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus (Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 37)</bibl>, which
		runs thus: “And Ulysses, having disfigured himself, comes as a spy to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, and being recognized by Helen he makes a compact
		with her concerning the capture of the city; and having slain some of the Trojans he arrives
		at the ships. And after these things he with Diomedes conveys the Palladium out of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>.” From this it appears that Ulysses made two
		different expeditions to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>: in one of them he went by himself as a spy in mean
		attire, and being recognized by Helen concerted with her measures for betraying <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> to the Greeks; in the other he went with Diomedes,
		and together the two stole the Palladium. The former of these expeditions is described by
		Homer in the <title>Odyssey</title> （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 4.242"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 4.242ff.</bibl>）, where Helen tells how Ulysses disfigured himself
		with wounds, and disguising himself in mean attire came as a beggar to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>; how she alone detected him, wormed the secrets of
		the Greeks out of him, and having sworn not to betray him till he had returned in safety to
		the ships, let him go free, whereupon on his way back he killed many Trojans. Euripides also
		relates this visit of Ulysses to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, adding that Helen revealed his presence to Hecuba,
		who spared his life and sent him out of the country （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hec. 239"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hec. 239-250</bibl>）. These two quite distinct expeditions of Ulysses
		have been confused and blended into one by Apollodorus. As to the joint expedition of
		Ulysses and Diomedes to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, and the stealing of the Palladium, see further <bibl
			default="NO">Conon 34</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica x.350-360</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. vi.311</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Malalas, Chr. v. pp. 109, 111ff., ed. L. Dindorf</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Zenobius, Cent. iii.8</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Apostolius, Cent. vi.15</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Suidas, s. vv. <foreign
				lang="greek">*diomh/deios a)na/gkh</foreign> and <foreign
				lang="greek">*palla/dion</foreign></bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hesychius, s.v. <foreign
				lang="greek">*diomh/deios a)na/gkh</foreign></bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Il. x.531, p. 822</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Plat. Rep. 6, 493b</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Verg. A. 2.162"
			valid="yes">Verg. A. 2.162-170</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 2.166"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 2.166</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis v.5, 8ff.</bibl> The narrative of Apollodorus suggests
		that Ulysses had the principal share in the exploit. But according to another and seemingly
		more prevalent tradition it was Diomedes who really bore off the image. This emerges
		particularly from Conon's account. Diomedes, he tells us, mounted on the shoulders of
		Ulysses, and having thus scaled the wall, he refused to draw his comrade up after him, and
		went in search of the Palladium. Having secured it, he returned with it to Ulysses, and
		together they retraced their steps to the Greek camp. But by the way the crafty Ulysses
		conceived the idea of murdering his companion and making himself master of the fateful
		image. So he dropped behind Diomedes and drew his sword. But the moon shone full; and as he
		raised his arm to strike, the flash of the blade in the moonlight caught the eye of the wary
		Diomedes. He faced round, drew his sword, and, upbraiding the other with his cowardice,
		drove him before him, while he beat the back of the recreant with the flat of his sword.
		This incident gave rise to the proverb, “Diomedes's compulsion,” applied to such as did what
		they were forced to do by dire necessity. The proverb is similarly explained by the other
		Greek proverb-writers and lexicographers cited above, except that, instead of the flash of
		the sword in the moonlight, they say it was the shadow of the sword raised to strike him
		which attracted the attention of Diomedes. The picturesque story appears to have been told
		in the <title>Little Iliad</title> （<bibl
			default="NO">Hesychius, s.v. <foreign
				lang="greek">*diomh/deios a)na/gkh</foreign></bibl>）. According to one account,
		Diomedes and Ulysses made their way into the Trojan citadel through a sewer （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 2.166"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 2.166</bibl>）, indeed a narrow and muddy sewer, as Sophocles
		called it in the play which he composed on the subject. See <bibl
			default="NO">Julius Pollux, ix.49</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, ii.36, frag.
			367</bibl>. Some affirmed that the Palladium was treacherously surrendered to the Greek
		heroes by Theano, the priestess of the goddess （<bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. vi.311</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Suidas, s.v. <foreign
				lang="greek">*palla/dion</foreign></bibl>）; to this step she was said to have been
		instigated by her husband Antenor （<bibl
			default="NO">Malalas, Chr. v. p. 109, ed. L. Dindorf</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis v.5, 8</bibl>）. As to Theano in her capacity of priestess,
		see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 6.297"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 6.297ff.</bibl> The theft of the Palladium furnished a not
		infrequent subject to Greek artists; but the artistic, like the literary, tradition was not
		agreed on the question whether the actual thief was Diomedes or Ulysses. See <bibl
			default="NO">Frazer on Paus. 1.22.6 （vol. ii. pp. 264 sq.）</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the stratagem of the Wooden Horse, by which <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> is said to have been captured, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 4.271"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 4.271-289</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 8.492"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 8.492-515</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 11.523"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11.523-532</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Lesches, Little Iliad, summarized by Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum
			Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 37</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Arctinus, Ilii Persis, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum
			Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 49</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xii.23-83, 104-156, 218-443, 539-585,
			xiii.21-59</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tryphiodorus, Excidium Ilii 57-541</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 629-723</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 930</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Verg. A. 2.13"
			valid="yes">Verg. A. 2.13-267</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 108</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis v.9, 11ff.</bibl> The story is only alluded to by Homer,
		but was no doubt fully told by Lesches and Arctinus, though of their narratives we possess
		only the brief abstracts of Proclus. The accounts of later writers, such as Virgil, Quintus
		Smyrnaeus, Tryphiodorus, Tzetzes, and Apollodorus himself, are probably based on the works
		of these early cyclic poets. The poem of Arctinus, if we may judge by Proclus's abstract,
		opened with the deliberations of the Trojans about the Wooden Horse, and from the similarity
		of the abstract to the text of Apollodorus we may infer that our author followed Arctinus
		generally, though not in all details; for instance, he differed from Arctinus in regard to
		the affair of Laocoon and his sons. See below. With the stratagem of the Wooden Horse we may
		compare the stratagem by which, in the war of Independence waged by the <placeName
			authname="tgn,7016845"
			key="tgn,7016845">United Provinces</placeName> against <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000095"
			key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName>, Prince Maurice contrived to make himself master of <placeName
			authname="tgn,7006827"
			key="tgn,7006827">Breda</placeName>. The city was then held by a Spanish garrison, which
		received its supply of fuel by boats. The master of one of these boats, Adrian Vandenberg by
		name, noticed that in the absence of the governor there was great negligence in conducting
		the examination to which all boats were subjected before they were allowed to enter the
		town. This suggested to Vandenberg a plan for taking the citadel by surprise. He
		communicated his plan to Prince Maurice, who readily embraced it. Accordingly the boat was
		loaded in appearance with turf as usual; but the turf was supported by a floor of planks
		fixed at the distance of several feet from the bottom; and beneath this floor seventy picked
		soldiers were placed under the command of an able officer named Harauguer. The boat had but
		a few miles to sail, yet through unexpected accidents several days passed before they could
		reach <placeName
			authname="tgn,7006827"
			key="tgn,7006827">Breda</placeName>. The wind veered against them, the melting ice （for
		it was the month of February） retarded their course, and the boat, having struck upon a
		bank, was so much damaged that the soldiers were for some time up to their knees in water.
		Their provisions were almost spent, and to add to their anxieties one of their number was
		seized with a violent cough, which, if it had continued, would inevitably have betrayed them
		to the enemy. The man generously entreated his comrades to kill him, offering them his own
		sword for the purpose; but they as generously refused, and happily the soldier's cough left
		him before they approached the walls. Even the leak in the boat was stopped by some
		accident. On reaching the fortifications the boat was searched, but only in the most
		superficial manner. Still the danger was great, for the turf was immediately purchased and
		the soldiers of the garrison set to work to unload it. They would soon have uncovered the
		planks and detected the ambush, if the ready-witted master of the boat had not first amused
		them with his discourse and then invited them to drink wine with him. The offer was readily
		accepted. The day wore on, darkness fell, and the Spanish soldiers were all drunk or asleep.
		At dead of night Harauguer and his men issued from the boat, and dividing into two bodies
		they attacked the guards and soon made themselves masters of two gates. Seized with a panic,
		the garrison fled the town. Prince Maurice marched in and took possession of the citadel.
		These events happened in the year <date
			authname="1590"
			value="1590">1590</date>. See <bibl
			default="NO">Robert Watson, <title>History of the Reign of Philip the Second</title>,
			4th ed. (London, 1785), bk. xxi. vol. iii. pp. 157-161</bibl>.</note>
	<note>According to Tzetzes the number of men who entered into the Wooden Horse was twenty-three,
		and he gives the names of them all （<bibl
			default="NO">Posthomerica 641-650</bibl>）. Quintus Smyrnaeus gives the names of thirty,
		and he says that there were more of them （<bibl
			default="NO">Posthomerica xii.314-335</bibl>）. He informs us that the maker of the
		horse, Epeus, entered last and drew up the ladder after him; and knowing how to open and
		shut the trapdoor, he sat by the bolt. To judge by Homer's description of the heroes in the
		Horse （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 11.526"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11. 526ff.</bibl>）, the hearts of most of them failed them, for
		they blubbered and their knees knocked together; but Neoptolemus never blenched and kept
		fumbling with the hilt of his sword.</note>
	<note>As to these deliberations of the Trojans, compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 8.505"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 8.505ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Arctinus, Ilii Persis, summarized by Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum
			Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 49</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tryphiodorus, Excidium Ilii 250ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Arctinus, Ilii Persis, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum
			Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 49</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dionysius of Halicarnassus, Ant. Rom. i.48.2</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xii.444-497</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 347</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Verg. A. 2.199"
			valid="yes">Verg. A. 2.199-227</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 135</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 2.201"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 2.201</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. pp. 144ff. （Second Vatican
			Mythographer 207）</bibl>. According to Arctinus, our oldest authority for the tragedy of
		Laocoon, the two serpents killed Laocoon himself and one of his sons. According to Virgil,
		Hyginus, and Servius, they killed Laocoon and both his sons. According to Quintus Smyrnaeus,
		the serpents killed the two sons but spared the father, who lived to lament their fate. This
		last seems to have been the version followed by Apollodorus. The reason of the calamity
		which befell Laocoon is explained by Servius on the authority of Euphorion. He tells us that
		when the Greek army landed in the <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002331"
			key="tgn,7002331">Troad</placeName>, the Trojans stoned the priest of Poseidon to death,
		because he had not, by offering sacrifices to the sea god, prevented the invasion.
		Accordingly, when the Greeks seemed to be departing, it was deemed advisable to sacrifice to
		Poseidon, no doubt in order to induce him to give the Greeks a stormy passage. But the
		priesthood was vacant, and it was necessary to choose a priest by lot. The lot fell on
		Laocoon, priest of the Thymbraean Apollo, but he had incurred the wrath of Apollo by
		sleeping with his wife in front of the divine image, and for this sacrilege he perished with
		his two sons. This narrative helps us to understand the statement of Apollodorus that the
		two serpents were sent by Apollo for a sign. According to Tzetzes, the death of Laocoon's
		son took place in the temple of the Thymbraean Apollo, the scene of the crime thus becoming
		the scene of the punishment. Sophocles wrote a tragedy on the subject of Laocoon, but though
		a few fragments of the play have survived, its contents are unknown. See <bibl
			default="NO">TGF (Nauck 2nd ed.), pp. 211ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C Pearson, vol. ii. pp.
			38ff.</bibl> In modern times the story of Laocoon is probably even better known from the
		wonderful group of statuary in the <placeName
			authname="tgn,7001168"
			key="tgn,7001168">Vatican</placeName> than from the verses of Virgil. That group, the
		work of three Rhodian sculptors, graced the palace of the emperor Titus in the time of
		Pliny, who declared that it was to be preferred to any other work either of sculpture or
		painting （<bibl
			default="NO">Pliny, Nat. Hist. xxxvi.37</bibl>）. Lessing took the group for the text of
		his famous essay on the comparative limitations of poetry and art.</note>
	<note>The beacon-light kindled by the deserter and traitor Sinon to guide the Greeks across the
		water to the doomed city is a regular feature in the narratives of the taking of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>; but the only other writer who mentions that it
		shone from the grave of Achilles is Tryphiodorus, who adds that all night long there blazed
		a light like the full moon above Helen's chamber, for she too was awake and signalling to
		the enemy, while all the town was plunged in darkness and silence; the sounds of revelry and
		music had died away, and not even the barking of a dog broke the stillness of the summer
		night. See <bibl
			default="NO">Tryphiodorus, Excidium Ilii 487-521</bibl>. That the poet conceived the
		fall of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> to have happened in the summer time is shown by his
		describing how the Trojans wreathed the mane of the Wooden Horse with flowers culled on
		river banks, and how the women spread carpets of roses under its feet （<bibl
			default="NO">Tryphiodorus, Excidium Ilii 316ff., 340-344</bibl>）. For these flowers of
		fancy Tryphiodorus is severely taken to task by the pedantic Tzetzes on the ground that <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> fell at midwinter; and he clinches the lesson
		administered to his predecessor by observing that he had learned from Orpheus, “who had it
		from another man,” never to tell a lie. Such was the state of the Higher Criticism at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Byzantium"
			key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName> in the twelfth century of our era. See <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 700-707</bibl>.</note>
	<note>This incident is derived from <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 4.274"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 4.274-289</bibl>. It is copied and told with fuller details by
		Tryphiodorus, who says that Anticlus expired under the iron grip of Ulysses （<bibl
			default="NO">Tryphiodorus, Excidium Ilii 463-490</bibl>）.</note>
	<note>As to the death of Priam at the altar, compare <bibl
			default="NO">Arctinus, Ilii Persis, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum
			Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 49</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Tro. 16"
			valid="yes">Eur. Tro. 16ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Tro. 481"
			valid="yes">Eur. Tro. 481-483</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hec. 22"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hec. 22-24</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 4.17.4"
			valid="yes">Paus. 4.17.4</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xiii.220-250</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tryphiodorus, Excidium Ilii 634-639</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 732ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Verg. A. 2.533"
			valid="yes">Verg. A. 2.533-558</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis v.12</bibl>. According to Lesches, the ruthless
		Neoptolemus dragged Priam from the altar and despatched him at his own door. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.27.2"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.27.2</bibl>, with <bibl
			default="NO">Frazer's note （vol. v. p. 371）</bibl>. The summary account of Proclus
		agrees almost verbally with the equally summary account of Apollodorus.</note>
	<note>Ulysses and Menelaus were bound by ties of hospitality to Antenor; for when they went as
		ambassadors to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> to treat of the surrender of Helen, he entertained
		them hospitably in his house. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 3.203"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 3.203-207</bibl>. Moreover, Antenor had advocated the surrender of
		Helen and her property to the Greeks. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 3.347"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 3.347-353</bibl>. According to Lesches, one of Antenor's sons,
		Lycaon, was wounded in the sack of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, but Ulysses recognized him and carried him safe out
		of the fray. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.26.8"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.26.8</bibl>. Sophocles composed a tragedy on the subject of Antenor
		and his sons, in which he said that at the storming of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> the Greeks hung a leopard's skin in front of
		Antenor's house in token that it was to be respected by the soldiery. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 13.1.53"
			valid="yes">Strab. 13.1.53</bibl>. In Polygnotus's great picture of the sack of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, which was one of the sights of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delphi"
			key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, the painter depicted the house of Antenor with
		the leopard's skin hung on the wall; in front of it were to be seen Antenor and his wife,
		with their children, including Glaucus, while beside them servants were lading an ass, to
		indicate the long journey which the exiles were about to undertake. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.27.3"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.27.3ff.</bibl> According to Roman tradition, Antenor led a colony
		of Enetians to the head of the Adriatic, where the people were thenceforth called Venetians （<bibl
			default="NO">Livy i.1</bibl>）. As to Sophocles's play, <title>The Antenorids</title>,
		see <bibl
			default="NO">TGF (Nauck 2nd ed.), p. 160</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, vol. i. pp.
			86ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Xen. Cyn. 1.15">Xen. Cyn. 1.15</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xiii.315-327</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Verg. A. 2.699"
			valid="yes">Verg. A. 2.699ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Arctinus, Ilii Persis, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum
			Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 49</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xiii.354ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tryphiodorus, Excidium Ilii 627-633</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 729-731</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis v.12</bibl>. Deiphobus had married Helen after the death
		of Paris. See above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. Epit. E.5.8"
			valid="yes">Apollod. E.5.8.9</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Arctinus, Ilii Persis, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum
			Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 50</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.25.8"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.25.8</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xiii.496-543</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Eur. Hec. 123</bibl> and <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Eur. Tro. 31</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis v.13</bibl>. Homer mentions Aethra as one of the handmaids
		of Helen at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 3.53"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 3.53</bibl>）. <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xiii.496-543</bibl> has described at length
		the recognition of the grandmother by the grandsons, who, according to Hellanicus, went to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> for the purpose of rescuing or ransoming her （<bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Eur. Hec. 123</bibl>）. The recognition was related also by
		Lesches （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.25.8"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.25.8</bibl>）. Aethra had been taken prisoner at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Athens"
			key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> by Castor and Pollux when they rescued their
		sister Helen. See above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. 3.7.4"
			valid="yes">Apollod. 3.7.4</bibl>, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. Epit. E.1.23"
			valid="yes">Apollod. E.1.23</bibl>. On the chest of Cypselus at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Olympia"
			key="perseus,Olympia">Olympia</placeName> the artist portrayed Helen setting her foot on
		Aethra's head and tugging at her handmaid's hair. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 5.19.3"
			valid="yes">Paus. 5.19.3</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dio Chrysostom xi. vol. i. p. 179, ed. L. Dindorf</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the violence offered to Cassandra by Ajax, compare <bibl
			default="NO">Arctinus, Ilii Persis, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum
			Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, pp. 49ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. xiii.66, referring to Callimachus</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 1.15.2"
			valid="yes">Paus. 1.15.2</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 5.11.6"
			valid="yes">Paus. 5.11.6</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 5.19.5"
			valid="yes">Paus. 5.19.5</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.26.3"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.26.3</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.31.2"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.31.2</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xiii.420-429</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tryphiodorus, Excidium Ilii 647-650</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Verg. A. 2.403"
			valid="yes">Verg. A. 2.403-406</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis v.12</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. p. 55 (First Vatican
			Mythographer 181)</bibl>. Arctinus described how, in dragging Cassandra from the image
		of Athena, at which she had taken refuge, Ajax drew down the image itself. This incident was
		carved on the chest of Cypselus at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Olympia"
			key="perseus,Olympia">Olympia</placeName> （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 5.19.5"
			valid="yes">Paus. 5.19.5</bibl>）, and painted by Polygnotus in his great picture of the
		sack of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delphi"
			key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.26.3"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.26.3</bibl>）. The <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. xiii.66</bibl> and Quintus Smyrnaeus describe how the
		image of Athena turned up its eyes to the roof in horror at the violence offered to the
		suppliant.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Arctinus, Ilii Persis, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum
			Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 50</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Tro. 719"
			valid="yes">Eur. Tro. 719-739</bibl>, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Tro. 1133"
			valid="yes">Eur. Tro. 1133-1135</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Andr. 8"
			valid="yes">Eur. And. 8-11</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.26.9"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.26.9</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xiii.251-257</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tryphiodorus, Excidium Ilii 644-646</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 1263</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Eur. Andr. 10</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Ov. Met. 13.415"
			valid="yes">Ov. Met. 13.415-417</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 109</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Seneca, Troades 524ff., 1063ff.</bibl> While ancient writers generally
		agree that Astyanax was killed by being thrown from a tower at or after the sack of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, they differ as to the agent of his death. Arctinus,
		as reported by Proclus, says merely that he was killed by Ulysses. Tryphiodorus reports that
		he was hurled by Ulysses from a high tower. On the other hand, Lesches in the <title>Little
			Iliad</title> said that it was Neoptolemus who snatched Astyanax from his mother's lap
		and cast him down from the battlements （Tzetzes and <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.26.9"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.26.9</bibl>）. According to Euripides and Seneca, the murder of the
		child was not perpetrated in hot blood during the sack of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> but was deliberately executed after the capture of
		the city in pursuance of a decree passed by the Greeks in a regular assembly. This seems to
		have been the version followed by Apollodorus, who apparently regarded the death of Astyanax
		as a sacrifice, like the slaughter of Polyxena on the grave of Achilles. But the killing of
		Astyanax was not thus viewed by our other ancient authorities, unless we except Seneca, who
		describes how Astyanax leaped voluntarily from the wall while Ulysses was reciting the words
		of the soothsayer Calchas and invoking the cruel gods to attend the rite.</note>
	<note>As to the sacrifice of Polyxena on the grave of Achilles, see <bibl
			default="NO">Arctinus, Ilii Persis, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum
			Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 50</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hec. 107"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hec. 107ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hec. 218"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hec. 218ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hec. 391"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hec. 391-393</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hec. 521"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hec. 521-582</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xiv.210-328</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tryphiodorus, Excidium Ilii 686ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 323</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 110</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Ov. Met. 13.439"
			valid="yes">Ov. Met. 13.439-480</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Seneca, Troades 168ff., 938-944, 1118-1164</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis v.13</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 3.322"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 3.322</bibl>. According to Euripides and Seneca, the ghost of
		Achilles appeared above his grave and demanded the sacrifice of the maiden. Others said that
		the spirit of the dead showed himself in a dream to Neoptolemus （so Quintus Smyrnaeus） or to
		Agamemnon （so Ovid）. In Quintus Smyrnaeus the ghost threatens to keep the Greeks wind-bound
		at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> until they have complied with his demand, and
		accordingly the offering of the sacrifice is followed by a great calm. Euripides seems to
		have contemplated the sacrifice, in primitive fashion, as a means of furnishing the ghost
		with the blood needed to quench his thirst （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hec. 391"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hec. 391-393</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hec. 536"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hec. 536ff.</bibl>）; but Seneca represents the ghost as desiring to
		have Polyxena as his wife in the Elysian Fields （<bibl
			default="NO">Seneca, Troades 938-944</bibl>）. A more romantic turn is given to the
		tradition by Philostratus, who says that after the death of Achilles, and before the fall of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, the amorous Polyxena stole out from the city and
		stabbed herself to death on the grave of Achilles, that she might be his bride in the other
		world. See <bibl
			default="NO">Philostratus, Her. xx.18</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Philostratus, Vit. Apollon. iv.16.4</bibl>. According to the usual
		tradition, it was Neoptolemus who slew the maiden on his father's tomb. Pictures of the
		sacrifice were to be seen at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Athens"
			key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and <placeName
			authname="perseus,Pergamon"
			key="perseus,Pergamon">Pergamus</placeName> （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 1.22.6"
			valid="yes">Paus. 1.22.6</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.25.10"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.25.10</bibl>）. Sophocles wrote a tragedy on the theme. See <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, vol. ii. pp.
			161ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xiv.20-23</bibl>, who agrees with
		Apollodorus as to the partition of these captive women among the Greek leaders.</note>
	<note>This is the version of the story adopted by Dares Phrygius, who says that Helenus went to
		the <placeName
			authname="tgn,1012789"
			key="tgn,1012789">Chersonese</placeName> along with Hecuba, Andromache, and Cassandra （<bibl
			default="NO">Dares Phrygius, De excidio Trojae 43</bibl>）.</note>
	<note>As to the transformation of Hecuba into a bitch, compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hec. 1259"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hec. 1259-1273</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xiv.347-351</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dio Chrysostom xxxii. vol. ii. p. 20, ed. L. Dindorf</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Agatharchides, De Erythraeo Mari, in Photius, Bibliotheca, p. 442a, ll.
			23ff., ed. Bekker</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Julius Pollux, v.45</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 315, 1176</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Excidium Ilii, Tusc. Disp. iii.26.63</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Ov. Met. 13.565"
			valid="yes">Ov. Met. 13.565-571</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 111</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 3.6"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 3.6</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. G.H.Bode, i. p. 145 （Second Vatican
			Mythographer 209）</bibl>. A rationalistic version of the story is told by <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis v.16</bibl>. We may conjecture that the fable of the
		transformation originated in the resemblance of the name Hecuba to the name Hecate; for
		Hecate was supposed to be attended by dogs, and Hecuba is called an attendant of Hecate （<bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 1176</bibl>）.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xiii.544-551</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tryphiodorus, Excidium Ilii 660-663</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Posthomerica 736</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 314</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Arctinus, Ilii Persis, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum
			Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, pp. 49ff.</bibl> Ulysses advised the Greeks to stone Ajax to
		death for his crime against Cassandra （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.31.2"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.31.2</bibl>）.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 3.130"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 3.130ff.</bibl>, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 3.276"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 3.276ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hagias, Returns, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta,
			ed. G. Kinkel, p. 53</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Hagias, Returns, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta,
			ed. G. Kinkel, p. 53</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 14.1.27"
			valid="yes">Strab. 14.1.27</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 427-430, 980</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 14.1.27"
			valid="yes">Strab. 14.1.27</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 427-430, 980</bibl>. From Strabo we learn
		that the riddle of Calchas concerning the wild fig-tree was recorded by Hesiod, and that the
		riddle of Mopsus concerning the sow was recorded by Pherecydes. Our authorities vary
		somewhat in regard to the latter riddle. According to Pherecydes, the true answer was,
		“Three little pigs, and one of them a female.” According to Tzetzes, Calchas could not solve
		the riddle, so Mopsus solved it by saying that the sow would farrow ten little pigs, of
		which one would be a male. Strabo also tells us that the oracle which doomed Calchas to
		death whenever he should meet a diviner more skilful than himself, was mentioned by
		Sophocles in his play <title>The Demand for Helen</title>. As to that play, see <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, vol. i. pp.
			121ff.</bibl> A different story of the rivalry of the two seers is told by <bibl
			default="NO">Conon 6</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the shipwreck and death of the Locrian Ajax, compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 4.499"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 4.499-511</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hagias, Returns, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta,
			ed. G. Kinkel, p. 53</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. xiii.66</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xiv.530-589</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 365, 387, 389, 402</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Verg. A. 1.39"
			valid="yes">Verg. A. 1.39-45</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 116</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Seneca, Agamemnon 532-556</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis vi.1</bibl>. In his great picture of the underworld, which
		Polygnotus painted at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delphi"
			key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, the artist depicted Ajax as a castaway, the
		brine forming a scurf on his skin （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.31.1"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.31.1</bibl>）. According to the <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. xiii.66</bibl> Ajax was cast up on the shore of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delos"
			key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>, where Thetis found and buried him. But as it was
		unlawful to be buried or even to die in <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delos"
			key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Thuc. 3.104"
			valid="yes">Thuc. 3.104</bibl>）, the statement of Apollodorus that Ajax was buried in
		Myconus, a small island to the east of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delos"
			key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>, is more probable. It is said that on hearing of
		his death the Locrians mourned for him and wore black for a year, and every year they laded
		a vessel with splendid offerings, hoisted a black sail on it, and, setting the ship on fire,
		let it drift out to sea, there to burn down to the water's edge as a sacrifice to the
		drowned hero. See <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 365</bibl>. Sophocles wrote a tragedy,
			<title>The Locrian Ajax</title>, on the crime and punishment of the hero. See <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, vol. i. pp.
			8ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>As to the false lights kindled by Nauplius to lure the Greek ships on to the breakers, see
		above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. 2.1.5"
			valid="yes">Apollod. 2.1.5</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hel. 766"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hel. 766ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hel. 1126"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hel. 1126ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Eur. Or. 432</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xiv.611-628</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 384</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Prop. 5.1.115"
			valid="yes">Prop. v.1.115ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 116</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Seneca, Agamemnon 557-575</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis vi.1</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 11.260"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 11.260</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Lactantius Placidus on Statius, Achill. i.93</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. pp. 46, 141 (First Vatican
			Mythographer 144; Second Vatican Mythographer 201)</bibl>. The story was probably told
		by Hagias in his epic <title>The Returns （Nostoi）</title>, though in the abstract of that
		poem there occurs merely a mention of “the storm at the Capherian Rocks.” See <bibl
			default="NO">Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 53</bibl>. The wrecker
		Nauplius was the subject of a tragedy by Sophocles. See <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, vol. ii. pp.
			80ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>As to the death of Palamedes, see above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. Epit. E.3.8"
			valid="yes">Apollod. E.3.8</bibl>.</note>
	<note>This passage, down to the end of Section 12, is quoted with some slight verbal changes,
		but without citing his authority, by <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 384-386</bibl>; compare <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 1093</bibl>.</note>
	<note>See Frazer's Appendix to Apollodorus, “The vow of Idomeneus.”</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Hagias, Returns, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta,
			ed. G. Kinkel, p. 53</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 902</bibl>, quoting “Apollodorus and the
		rest.” According to <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 2.166"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 2.166</bibl>, it was the soothsayer Helenus who, foreseeing
		the shipwreck of the Greek leaders, warned Neoptolemus to return home by land; hence in
		gratitude for this benefit Neoptolemus at his death bequeathed Andromache to Helenus to be
		his wife （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 3.297"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 3.297</bibl>）. Neoptolemus was on friendly terms with
		Helenus, because the seer had revealed to the Greeks the means by which <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> could be taken, and because in particular he had
		recommended the fetching of Neoptolemus himself from Scyros. See above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. Epit. E.5.10"
			valid="yes">Apollod. E.5.10</bibl>. A different tradition is recorded by <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Od. 3.189, p. 1463</bibl>. He says that Neoptolemus
		sailed across the sea to <placeName
			authname="tgn,7001399"
			key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName> and there burned his ships by the advice of
		Thetis; after which, being directed by the soothsayer Helenus to settle wherever he should
		find a house with foundations of iron, walls of wood, and roof of wool, he marched inland
		till he came to the lake Pambotis in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002705"
			key="tgn,7002705">Epirus</placeName>, where he fell in with some people camping under
		blankets supported by spears, of which the blades were stuck into the earth. Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Od. iii.188</bibl>, who adds that, “having laid waste
		Molossia, he begot Molossus by Andromache, and from Molossus is descended the race of the
		kings of Molossia, as Eratosthenes relates.” The lake Pambotis is believed to be what is now
		called the lake of Joannina, near which <placeName
			authname="perseus,Dodona"
			key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> was situated. <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 1.11.1"
			valid="yes">Paus. 1.11.1</bibl> mentions that Pyrrhus （Neoptolemus） settled in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002705"
			key="tgn,7002705">Epirus</placeName> “in compliance with the oracles of Helenus,” and
		that he had Molossus, Pielus, and Pergamus by Andromache.</note>
	<note>As to Deidamia, mother of Neoptolemus, see above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. 3.13.8"
			valid="yes">Apollod. 3.13.8</bibl>. The marriage of Helenus to Deidamia appears not to
		be mentioned by any other ancient writer.</note>
	<note>According to <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Tro. 1126"
			valid="yes">Eur. Tro. 1126-1130</bibl>, while Neoptolemus was still at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, he heard that his grandfather Peleus had been
		expelled by Acastus; hence he departed for home in haste, taking Andromache with him. The
		Scholiast on this passage of Euripides (<date
			authname="1128"
			value="1128">1128</date>) says that Peleus was expelled by Acastus's two sons, Archander
		and Architeles, and that the exiled king, going to meet his grandson Neoptolemus, was driven
		by a storm to the island of Cos, where he was entertained by a certain Molon and died. As to
		an early connexion between <placeName
			authname="tgn,7001399"
			key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName> and Cos, see <bibl
			default="NO">W. R. Paton and E. L. Hicks, <title>The Inscriptions of Cos</title>, pp.
			344ff.</bibl> A different and much more detailed account of the exile of Peleus is
		furnished by <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis vi.7-9</bibl>. According to it, when Neoptolemus was
		refitting his shattered ships in Molossia, he heard that Peleus had been deposed and
		expelled by Acastus. Hastening to the aid of his aged grandfather, he found him hiding in a
		dark cave on the shore of one of the Sepiades Islands, where he eagerly scanned every
		passing sail in hopes that one of them would bring his grandson to his rescue. By disguising
		himself Neoptolemus contrived to attack and kill Acastus's two sons, Menalippus and
		Plisthenes, when they were out hunting. Afterwards, disguising himself as a Trojan captive,
		he lured Acastus himself to the cave and would have slain him there, if it had not been for
		the intercession of Thetis, who had opportunely arrived from the sea to visit her old
		husband Peleus. Happy at his escape, Acastus resigned the kingdom on the spot to
		Neoptolemus, and that hero at once took possession of the realm in company with his
		grandfather, his divine grandmother Thetis, and the companions of his voyage. This romantic
		narrative may be based on a lost Greek tragedy, perhaps on the <title>Peleus</title> of
		Sophocles, a play in which the dramatist appears to have dealt with the fortunes of Peleus
		in his old age. See <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, vol. ii. pp.
			140ff.</bibl> The statement of Dictys Cretensis that Peleus took refuge in one of the
		Sepiades Islands suggests that in the <bibl
			default="NO">Scholium on Eur. Tro. 1126-1130</bibl> the name Icos should be read instead
		of Cos, as has been argued by several scholars （<bibl
			default="NO">A. C. Pearson, op. cit. ii.141</bibl>）; for Icos was a small island near <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002677"
			key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> （<bibl
			default="NO">Stephanus Byzantius, s.v. <foreign
				lang="greek">*)iko/s</foreign></bibl>）, and would be a much more natural place of
		refuge for Peleus than the far more distant island of Cos. Moreover, we have the positive
		affirmation of the poet Antipater of <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002861"
			key="tgn,7002861">Sidon</placeName> that Peleus was buried in Icos （<bibl
			default="NO">Anth. Pal. vii.2.9ff.</bibl>）. The connexion of Peleus with the Sepiades
		Islands is further supported by Euripides; for in his play <title>Andromache</title> （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Andr. 1253"
			valid="yes">Eur. And. 1253-1269</bibl>） he tells how Thetis bids her old husband Peleus
		tarry in a cave of these islands, till she should come with a band of Nereids to fetch him
		away, that he might dwell with her as a god for ever in the depths of the sea. In the same
		play （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Andr. 22"
			valid="yes">Eur. And. 22ff.</bibl>） Euripides says that Neoptolemus refused to accept
		the sceptre of Pharsalia in the lifetime of his grandfather Peleus.</note>
	<note>In this passage Apollodorus appears to follow the account given by Euripides in his
			<title>Andromache</title>, (<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Andr. 967"
			valid="yes">Eur. And. 967-981</bibl>). According to that account, Menelaus gave his
		daughter Hermione in marriage to her cousin Orestes, the son of Agamemnon and Clytaemnestra.
		But in the Trojan war he afterwards promised the hand of Hermione to Neoptolemus, if
		Neoptolemus should succeed in capturing <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. Accordingly on his return from the war Neoptolemus
		claimed his bride from her husband Orestes, who was then haunted and maddened by the Furies
		of his murdered mother Clytaemnestra. Orestes protested, but in vain; Neoptolemus insolently
		reproached him with his crime of matricide and with the unseen avengers of blood by whom he
		was pursued. So Orestes was obliged to yield up his wife to his rival, but he afterwards
		took his revenge by murdering Neoptolemus at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delphi"
			key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>. This version of the legend is followed also by <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 123</bibl>. An obvious difficulty is presented by the
		narrative; for if Menelaus had given his daughter in marriage to Orestes, how could he
		afterwards have promised her to Neoptolemus in the lifetime of her first husband? This
		difficulty was met by another version of the story, which alleged that Hermione was
		betrothed or married to Orestes by her grandfather Tyndareus in the absence of her father
		Menelaus, who was then away at the Trojan war; that meantime, in ignorance of this disposal
		of his daughter, Menelaus had promised her hand to Neoptolemus before <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, and that on his return from the war Neoptolemus
		took her by force from Orestes. See <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Od. iv.3, p. 1479</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Od. iv.4</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Ovid, Her. viii.31ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 3.330"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 3.330, compare on 297</bibl>. According to the tragic poet
		Philocles, not only had Hermione been given in marriage by Tyndareus to Orestes, but she was
		actually with child by Orestes when her father afterwards married her to Neoptolemus. See <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Eur. Andr. 32</bibl>. This former marriage of Hermione to
		Orestes, before she became the wife of Neoptolemus, is recognized by <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Verg. A. 3.330"
			valid="yes">Verg. A. 3.330</bibl>, and <bibl
			default="NO">Ovid, Heroides, viii. passim</bibl>, but it is unknown to Homer. On the
		other hand, Homer records that Menelaus betrothed Hermione to Neoptolemus at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, and celebrated the marriage after his return to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Sparta"
			key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 4.1"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 4.1-9</bibl>）. Sophocles wrote a tragedy <title> Hermione </title>,
		the plot of which seems to have resembled that of the <title>Andromache</title> of
		Euripides. See <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, vol. ii. pp.
			141ff.</bibl> Euripides does not appear to have been consistent in his view that
		Neoptolemus forcibly deprived Orestes of Hermione and married her himself; for in his play
		Orestes （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Orest. 1653"
			valid="yes">Eur. Or. 1653-1657</bibl>） he makes Apollo prophesy to Orestes that he shall
		wed Hermione, but that Neoptolemus shall never do so.</note>
	<note>The murder of Neoptolemus at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delphi"
			key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, as Apollodorus observes, was variously related.
		According to Euripides, Neoptolemus paid two visits to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delphi"
			key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>. On the first occasion he went to claim redress
		from Apollo, who had shot his father Achilles at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> （see above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. Epit. E.5.3"
			valid="yes">Apollod. E.5.3</bibl>）. On the second occasion he went to excuse himself to
		the god for the rashness and impiety of which he had been guilty in calling the deity to
		account for the murder; and it was then that Orestes, enraged at having been robbed of his
		wife Hermione by Neoptolemus, waylaid and murdered his rival in the temple of Apollo, the
		fatal blow being struck, however, not by Orestes but by “a Delphian man.” See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Andr. 49"
			valid="yes">Eur. And. 49-55</bibl>, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Andr. 1086"
			valid="yes">Eur. And. 1086-1165</bibl>; compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Orest. 1656"
			valid="yes">Eur. Or. 1656ff.</bibl> This is the version of the story which Apollodorus
		appears to prefer. It is accepted also by <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 123</bibl>, <bibl
			default="NO">Velleius Paterculus i.1.3</bibl>, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 3.297"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 3.297, 330</bibl>, and somewhat ambiguously by <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis vi.12ff.</bibl> The murder of Neoptolemus by Orestes is
		mentioned, but without any motive assigned, by <bibl
			default="NO">Heliodorus ii.34</bibl> and <bibl
			default="NO">Justin xvii.3.7</bibl>. A different account is given by Pindar. He says
		that Neoptolemus went to consult the god at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delphi"
			key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, taking with him first-fruit offerings of the
		Trojan spoil; that there he was stabbed to death by a man in a brawl concerning the flesh of
		the victim, and that after death he was supposed to dwell within the sacred precinct and to
		preside over the processions and sacrifices in honour of heroes. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Pind. N. 7"
			valid="yes">Pind. N. 7.34(50)-47(70)</bibl>; compare <bibl
			default="NO">Pind. Pa. 6.117ff.</bibl>P The Scholiast on the former of these passages of
		Pindar, <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Pind. Pa. 42(62)</bibl>, explains the brawl by saying that it
		was the custom of the Delphians to appropriate （<foreign
			lang="greek">a(rpa/zein</foreign>） the sacrifices; that Neoptolemus attempted to prevent
		them from taking possession of his offerings, and that in the squabble the Delphians
		despatched him with their swords. This explanation seems to be due to Pherecydes, for a <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Eur. Or. 1655</bibl> quotes the following passage from that
		early historian: “When Neoptolemus married Hermione, daughter of Menelaus, he went to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delphi"
			key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> to inquire about offspring; for he had no
		children by Hermione. And when at the oracle he saw the Delphians scrambling for （<foreign
			lang="greek">diarpa/zontas</foreign>） the flesh, he attempted to take it from them. But
		their priest Machaereus killed him and buried him under the threshold of the temple.” This
		seems to have been the version of the story followed by Pausanias, for he mentions the
		hearth at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delphi"
			key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> on which the priest of Apollo slew Neoptolemus （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.24.4"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.24.4</bibl>）, and elsewhere he says that “the Pythian priestess
		ordered the Delphians to kill Pyrrhus （Neoptolemus）, son of Achilles” （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 1.13.9"
			valid="yes">Paus. 1.13.9</bibl>; compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 4.17.4"
			valid="yes">Paus. 4.17.4</bibl>）. That the slayer of Neoptolemus was called Machaereus
		is mentioned also by a <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Eur. Andr. 53</bibl> and by <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 9.3.9"
			valid="yes">Strab. 9.3.9</bibl>, who says that Neoptolemus was killed “because he
		demanded satisfaction from the god for the murder of his father, or, more probably, because
		he had made an attack on the sanctuary.” Indeed, Asclepiades, in his work
			<title>Tragodoumena</title>, wrote as follows: “About his death almost all the poets
		agree that he was killed by Machaereus and buried at first under the threshold of the
		temple, but that afterwards Menelaus came and took up his body, and made his grave in the
		precinct. He says that Machaereus was a son of Daetas.” See <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Pind. N. 7.42(62)</bibl>. The story that Neoptolemus came to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delphi"
			key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> to plunder the sanctuary, which is noticed by
		Apollodorus and preferred by Strabo, is mentioned by <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.7.1"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.7.1</bibl> and a <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Pind. N. 7.58, Boeckh</bibl>. It is probably not inconsistent
		with the story that he went to demand satisfaction from, or to inflict punishment on, the
		god for the death of his father; for the satisfaction or punishment would naturally take the
		shape of a distress levied on the goods and chattels of the defaulting deity. The tradition
		that the slain Neoptolemus was buried under the threshold of Apollo's temple is remarkable
		and, so far as I remember, unique in Greek legend. The statement that the body was
		afterwards taken up and buried within the precinct agrees with the observation of <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.24.6"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.24.6</bibl> that “quitting the temple and turning to the left you
		come to an enclosure, inside of which is the grave of Neoptolemus, son of Achilles. The
		Delphians offer sacrifice to him annually as to a hero.” From <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Pind. N. 7"
			valid="yes">Pind. N. 7.44(65)ff.</bibl> we learn that Neoptolemus even enjoyed a
		preeminence over other heroes at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delphi"
			key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, being called on to preside over the processions
		and sacrifices in their honour. The Aenianes of <placeName
			authname="tgn,7001399"
			key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName> used to send a grand procession and costly
		sacrifices to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delphi"
			key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> every fourth year in honour of Neoptolemus. The
		ceremony fell at the same time as the Pythian games. See <bibl
			default="NO">Heliodorus, Aeth. ii.34-iii.6</bibl>. It is a little difficult to
		understand how a man commonly accused of flagrant impiety and sacrilege should have been
		raised to such a pitch of glory at the very shrine which he was said to have attacked and
		robbed. The apparent contradiction might be more intelligible if we could suppose that, as
		has been suggested, Neoptolemus was publicly sacrificed as a scapegoat, perhaps by being
		stoned to death, as seems to have been the fate of the human victims at the Thargelia, whose
		sacrifice was justified by a legend that the first of their number had stolen some sacred
		cups of Apollo. See <bibl
			default="NO">Harpocration, s.v. <foreign
				lang="greek">fa/rmakos</foreign></bibl>; and as to the suggestion that Neoptolemus
		may have been sacrificed as a scapegoat, see <bibl
			default="NO">J. Toepffer, “Thargelienbrauche,” <title>Beiträge zur griechischen
				Altertumswissenschaft</title> （Berlin, 1897）, pp. 132ff.</bibl>, who points out that
		according to <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Andr. 1127"
			valid="yes">Eur. And. 1127ff.</bibl> Neoptolemus was stoned as well as stabbed at the
		altar of Apollo. As to the custom of burying the dead under a threshold, see <bibl
			default="NO"><title>Folk-Lore in the Old Testament</title>, iii.13ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>The wanderings described in the remainder of this paragraph, except those of Agapenor, are
		resumed and told somewhat more fully in the following three paragraphs （15a, 15b, 15c）,
		which do not occur in our text of the <title>Epitome</title>, but are conjecturally restored
		to it from the Scholiast on Lycophron of Tzetzes, who probably had before him the full text
		of Apollodorus, and not merely the <title>Epitome</title>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 8.5.2"
			valid="yes">Paus. 8.5.2</bibl>, who says that, driven by the storm to <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000112"
			key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>, Agapenor founded <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002373"
			key="tgn,7002373">Paphos</placeName> and built the sanctuary of Aphrodite at Old Paphos.
		Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aristot. Pepl. 30">Aristot. Peplos 30(16), in Bergk's <title>Poetae Lyrici
				Graeci</title>, ii.654</bibl>.</note>
	<note>This paragraph is quoted from <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 902</bibl>.</note>
	<note>According to another account, Guneus was drowned at sea. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aristot. Pepl. 32">Aristot. Peplos 32(37), in Bergk's <title>Poetae Lyrici
				Graeci</title>, ii.654</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Epitaphs on these two drowned men are ascribed to <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aristot. Pepl. 25">Aristot. Peplos 25(19)</bibl> and <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aristot. Pepl. 28">28(38)</bibl>. See <bibl
			default="NO"><title>Bergk's Poetae Lyrici Graeci</title>, ii.653, 654</bibl>. Meges was
		leader of the Dulichians, and Prothous was leader of the Magnesians. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. Epit. E.3.12"
			valid="yes">Apollod. E.3.12</bibl> and <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. Epit. E.14"
			valid="yes">Apollod. E.14</bibl>.</note>
	<note>This paragraph is quoted from <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 911</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 9.5.23"
			valid="yes">Strab. 9.5.23</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Elephenor was killed in battle by Agenor. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 4.463"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 4.463-472</bibl>. Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aristot. Pepl. 33">Aristot. Peplos 33(4), in Bergk's <title>Poetae Lyrici
				Graeci</title>, ii.654</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Canastrum, or Canastra, is the extreme southern cape of the peninsula of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Pallene"
			key="perseus,Pallene">Pallene</placeName> （<placeName
			authname="perseus,Pellene"
			key="perseus,Pellene">Pellene</placeName>） in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7006667"
			key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hdt. 7.123"
			valid="yes">Hdt. 7.123</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Ap. Rhod., Argon. i.599, with the Scholiast</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 7.fragments.25"
			valid="yes">Strab. 7 Fr. 25</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Apostolius, Cent. ii.20</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 526</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Livy xxx.45.15, xliv.11.3</bibl>.</note>
	<note>It is said that in a sedition Philoctetes was driven from his city of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Meliboea"
			key="perseus,Meliboea">Meliboea</placeName> in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7001399"
			key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName> （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Il. 2.717"
			valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.717ff.</bibl>）, and fled to southern <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000080"
			key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, where he founded the cities of Petilia, Old
		Crimissa, and Chone, between <placeName
			authname="perseus,Croton"
			key="perseus,Croton">Croton</placeName> and <placeName
			authname="perseus,Thurii"
			key="perseus,Thurii">Thurii</placeName>. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 6.1.3"
			valid="yes">Strab. 6.1.3</bibl>, who, after recording the foundation of Petilia and Old
		Crimissa by Philoctetes, proceeds as follows: “And Apollodorus, after mentioning Philoctetes
		in his <title>Book of the Ships</title>, says that some people relate how, on arriving in
		the country of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Croton"
			key="perseus,Croton">Croton</placeName>, he founded Crimissa on the headland and above
		it the city of Chone, from which the Chonians hereabout took their name, and how men sent by
		him to <placeName
			authname="tgn,7003122"
			key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> fortified Segesta near <placeName
			authname="perseus,Eryx"
			key="perseus,Eryx">Eryx</placeName> with the help of Aegestes the Trojan.” The book from
		which Strabo makes this quotation is not the <title>Library</title> of our author, but the
			<title>Catalogue of the Ships</title>, a work on the Homeric Catalogue by the Athenian
		grammarian Apollodorus. According to <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 8.3.6"
			valid="yes">Strab. 8.3.6</bibl>, Apollodorus borrowed most of his materials for this
		work from Demetrius of Scepsis. For the fragments of the work see <bibl
			default="NO">Heyne's Apollodorus （Second Edition, 1803）, vol. i. pp. 417ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Fragmenta Historicorum Graecorum, ed. C. Müller, i.453ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aristot. Mir. 107">Aristot. Mir. 107(115)</bibl>: “It is said that Philoctetes is
		worshipped by the Sybarites; for on his return from <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> he settled in the territory of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Croton"
			key="perseus,Croton">Croton</placeName> at the place called Macalla, which they say is
		distant a hundred and twenty furlongs, and they relate that he dedicated the bow of Hercules
		in the sanctuary of the Halian Apollo. But they say that in the time of their sovereignty
		the people of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Croton"
			key="perseus,Croton">Croton</placeName> fetched the bow from there and dedicated it in
		the sanctuary of Apollo in their country. It is said, too, that when he died he was buried
		beside the river <placeName
			authname="perseus,Sybaris"
			key="perseus,Sybaris">Sybaris</placeName>; for he had gone to the help of the Rhodians
		under Tlepolemus, who had been carried out of their course to these regions and had engaged
		in battle with the barbarous inhabitants of that country.” This war with the barbarians is
		no doubt the “war on the Lucanians,” in which Apollodorus, or at all events, Tzetzes here
		tells us that Philoctetes engaged after his arrival in <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000080"
			key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>.</note>
	<note>This paragraph is quoted from <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 921</bibl>.</note>
	<note>The same story is told by Strabo, who calls the river Neaethus （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 6.1.12"
			valid="yes">Strab. 6.1.12</bibl>）. Stephanus Byzantius agrees with Apollodorus in giving
		Navaethus （<foreign
			lang="greek">*nau/aiqos</foreign>） as the form of the name. Apollodorus derives the name
		from <foreign
			lang="greek">nau=s</foreign>, “a ship,” and <foreign
			lang="greek">ai)/qw</foreign>, “to burn.” Virgil tells a similar tale of the founding of
		Segesta or, as he calls it, Acesta in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7003122"
			key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Verg. A. 5.604"
			valid="yes">Verg. A. 5.604-771</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Demophon and his brother Acamas, the sons of Theseus, had gone to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> to rescue their grandmother Aethra from captivity.
		See above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. Epit. E.5.22"
			valid="yes">Apollod. E.5.22</bibl>. The following story of the loves and sad fate of
		Demophon and Phyllis is told in almost the same words by <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 495</bibl>, except that for the name of
		Demophon he substitutes the name of his brother Acamas. Lucian also couples the names of
		Acamas and Phyllis （<bibl
			default="NO">Lucian, De saltatione 40</bibl>）. A pretty story is told of the sad lovers
		by Servius. He says that Phyllis, despairing of the return of Demophon, hanged herself and
		was turned into a leafless almond tree; but that when Demophon came and embraced the trunk
		of the tree, it responded to his endearments by bursting into leaf; hence leaves, which had
		been called <foreign
			lang="greek">pe/tala</foreign> before, were ever after called <foreign
			lang="greek">fu/lla</foreign> in Greek. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. Ecl. 5.10"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. Ecl. 5.10</bibl>. Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. pp. 51, 146ff. (First
			Vatican Mythographer 159; Second Vatican Mythographer 214)</bibl>. The story is told in
		a less romantic form by <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 59</bibl>, compare 243. He says that when Phyllis died for
		love, trees grew on her grave and mourned her death at the season when their leaves withered
		and fell.</note>
	<note>The same story is told, nearly in the same words, by <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes （Scholiast on Lycophron 1047）</bibl>, who probably copied
		Apollodorus. As to the settlement of Podalirius in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002358"
			key="tgn,7002358">Caria</placeName>, compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 3.26.10"
			valid="yes">Paus. 3.26.10</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Stephanus Byzantius, s.v. <foreign
				lang="greek">*su/rna</foreign></bibl>. Podalirius was worshipped as a hero in <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000080"
			key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>. He had a shrine at the foot of Mount Drium in
		Daunia, and the seer Calchas was worshipped in a shrine on the top of the same mountain,
		where his worshippers sacrificed black rams and slept in the skins of the victims for the
		purpose of receiving revelations in dreams. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 6.3.9"
			valid="yes">Strab. 6.3.9</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Lycophron, Cassandra 1047ff.</bibl> Hence Lycophron said that Podalirius
		was buried in <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000080"
			key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, and for so saying he was severely taken to task by
		his learned but crabbed commentator Tzetzes, who roundly accused him of lying （<bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Lycophron 1047</bibl>）.</note>
	<note>This passage is quoted from Apollodorus, with the author's name, by <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes （Scholiast on Lycophron 440-442）</bibl>, who says that according to
		the usual tradition Amphilochus and Mopsus had gone together to <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002470"
			key="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName> after the capture of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. This statement is confirmed by the testimony of <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 14.5.16"
			valid="yes">Strab. 14.5.16</bibl>, who tells us that Amphilochus and Mopsus came from <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> and founded <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002594"
			key="tgn,7002594">Mallus</placeName> in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002470"
			key="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName>. The dispute between Amphilochus and Mopsus is
		related more fully both by <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes （Scholiast on Lycophron 440-442）</bibl> and <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 14.5.16"
			valid="yes">Strab. 14.5.16</bibl> According to them, Amphilochus wished to go for a time
		to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Argos"
			key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> （probably <placeName
			authname="perseus,Amphilochian Argos"
			key="perseus,Amphilochian Argos">Amphilochian Argos</placeName>; see above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. 3.7.7"
			valid="yes">Apollod. 3.7.7</bibl>）. So he departed after entrusting the kingdom or
		priesthood to Mopsus in his absence. Dissatisfied with the state of affairs at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Argos"
			key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, he returned in a year and reclaimed the kingdom
		or priesthood from Mopsus. But, acting on the principle <foreign
			lang="la">Beati possidentes</foreign>, the viceroy refused to cede the crown or the
		mitre to its proper owner; accordingly they had recourse to the ordeal of battle, in which
		both combatants perished. Their bodies were buried in graves which could not be seen from
		each other; for the people built a tower between them, in order that the rivals, who had
		fought each other in life, might not scowl at each other in death. However, their rivalry
		did not prevent them working an oracle in partnership after their decease. In the second
		century of our era the oracle enjoyed the highest reputation for infallibility （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 1.34.3"
			valid="yes">Paus. 1.34.3</bibl>）. The leading partner of the firm was apparently
		Amphilochus, for he is usually mentioned alone in connexion with the oracle; <bibl
			default="NO">Plut. De defectu oraculorum 45</bibl> is the only ancient writer from whom
		we learn that Mopsus took an active share in the business though Cicero mentions the
		partners together （<bibl
			default="NO">Cicero, De divinatione i.40.88</bibl>）. According to Plutarch and <bibl
			default="NO">Dio Cassius lxxii.7</bibl>, the oracles were communicated in dreams; but
		Lucian says （<bibl
			default="NO">Philopseudes 38</bibl>） that the inquirer wrote down his question on a
		tablet, which he handed to the prophet. The charge for one of these infallible
		communications was only two obols, or about twopence halfpenny. See <bibl
			default="NO">Lucian, Alexander 19</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Lucian, Deorum concilium 12</bibl>. The ancients seem to have been divided
		in opinion on the important question whether the oracular Amphilochus at <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002594"
			key="tgn,7002594">Mallus</placeName> was the son or the grandson of Amphiaraus.
		Apollodorus calls him the son of Alcmaeon, which would make him the grandson of Amphiaraus,
		for Alcmaeon was a son of Amphiaraus. But Tzetzes, in reporting what he describes as the
		usual version of the story, calls Amphilochus the son, not the grandson of Amphiaraus （<bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Lycophron 440-442</bibl>）. Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 14.1.27"
			valid="yes">Strab. 14.1.27</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Posthomerica xiv.365-369</bibl>. Lucian is inconsistent
		on the point; for while in one passage he calls Amphilochus the son of Amphiaraus （<bibl
			default="NO">Lucian, Alexander 19</bibl>）, in another passage he speaks of him
		sarcastically as the noble son of an accurst matricide, by whom he means Alcmaeon （<bibl
			default="NO">Quintus Smyrnaeus, Deorum concilium 12</bibl>）. Elsewhere Apollodorus
		mentions both Amphilochus, the son of Amphiaraus, and Amphilochus, the son of Alcmaeon. See
		above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. 3.7.2"
			valid="yes">Apollod. 3.7.2</bibl> and <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. 3.7.7"
			valid="yes">Apollod. 3.7.7</bibl>.</note>
	<note>The story of the custom of propitiating Athena at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> by sending two Locrian virgins to her every year is
		similarly told by Tzetzes, who adds some interesting particulars omitted by Apollodorus.
		From him we learn that when the maidens arrived, the Trojans met them and tried to catch
		them. If they caught the maidens, they killed them and burned their bones with the wood of
		wild trees which bore no fruit. Having done so, they threw the ashes from Mount Traron into
		the sea. But if the maidens escaped from their pursuers, they ascended secretly to the
		sanctuary of Athena and became her priestesses, sweeping and sprinkling the sacred precinct;
		but they might not approach the goddess, nor quit the sanctuary except by night. Tzetzes
		agrees with Apollodorus in describing the maidens during their term of service as barefoot,
		with cropped hair, and clad each in a single tunic. He refers to the Sicilian historian
		Timaeus as his authority for the statement that the custom was observed for a thousand
		years, and that it came to an end after the Phocian war （<dateRange
			authname="-357/-346"
			from="-357"
			to="-346">357</dateRange>-346 B.C.）. See <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 1141</bibl>. The maidens were chosen by lot
		from the hundred noblest families in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7010899"
			key="tgn,7010899">Locris</placeName> （<bibl
			default="NO">Polybius xii.5</bibl>）; and when they escaped death on landing, they served
		the goddess in the sanctuary for the term of their lives （<bibl
			default="NO">Plut. De sera numinis vindicta 12</bibl>）, or, at all events, till their
		successors arrived （<bibl
			default="NO">Suidas, s.v. <foreign
				lang="greek">kategh/rasan</foreign></bibl>）. For other references to this very
		remarkable custom, which appears to be well authenticated, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 13.1.40"
			valid="yes">Strab. 13.1.40</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Il. xiii.66</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Iamblichus, De Pythagorica vita, viii.42</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Suidas, s.v. <foreign
				lang="greek">poinh/</foreign> （quoting Aelian）</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 1.41"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 1.41</bibl>. Servius, in contradiction to our other
		authorities, says that only one maiden was sent annually. Strabo appears to affirm that the
		custom originated as late as the Persian period （<foreign
			lang="greek">ta\s de\ Lokri/das pemfqh=nai Persw=n h)/dh kratou/ntwn sune/bh）.</foreign>
		This view is accepted by Clinton, who accordingly holds that the custom lasted from <date
			authname="-559"
			value="-559">559</date> B.C. to <date
			authname="-346"
			value="-346">346</date> B.C.（<bibl
			default="NO">Fasti Hellenici, i.134ff.</bibl>）.</note>
	<note>As to the murder of Agamemnon, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 3.193"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 3.193ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 3.303"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 303-305</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 4.529"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 4.529-537</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 11.404"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11.404-434</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hagias, Returns, summarized by Proclus, in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta,
			ed. G. Kinkel, p. 53</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aesch. Ag. 1379"
			valid="yes">Aesch. Ag. 1379ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aesch. Eum. 631"
			valid="yes">Aesch. Eum. 631-635</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Soph. El. 95"
			valid="yes">Soph. Elec. 95-99</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. El. 8"
			valid="yes">Eur. El. 8-10</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Orest. 25"
			valid="yes">Eur. Or. 25ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 2.16.6"
			valid="yes">Paus. 2.16.6</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 1108, 1375</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 117</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Seneca, Agamemnon 875-909</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 11.268"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 11.268</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. pp. 47, 126, 141ff. (First
			Vatican Mythographer 147; Second Vatican Mythographer 147, 202)</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis vi.2</bibl>. According to Homer and the author of the
			<title>Returns</title>, with whom Pausanias agrees, it was Aegisthus who killed
		Agamemnon; according to Aeschylus, it was Clytaemnestra. Sophocles and Euripides speak of
		the murder being perpetrated by the two jointly. The sleeveless and neckless garment in
		which Clytaemnestra entangled her husband, while she cut him down, is described with tragic
		grandiloquence and vagueness by Aeschylus, but more explicitly by later writers （Tzetzes,
		Seneca, Servius and the Vatican Mythographers）.</note>
	<note>As to the murder of Cassandra, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 11.421"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11.421-423</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Pind. P. 11"
			valid="yes">Pind. P. 11.19(29)ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Philostratus, Im. ii.10</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Athenaeus xiii.3, p. 556 C</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 117</bibl>. According to Hyginus, both Clytaemnestra and
		Aegisthus had a hand in the murder of Cassandra; according to the other writers, she was
		despatched by Clytaemnestra alone.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Pind. P. 11"
			valid="yes">Pind. P. 11.34(52)ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Soph. El. 11"
			valid="yes">Soph. Elec. 11ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. El. 14"
			valid="yes">Eur. El. 14ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 117</bibl>. Pindar tells how, after the murder of his father
		Agamemnon, the youthful Orestes was conveyed to the aged Strophius at the foot of <placeName
			authname="tgn,7011022"
			key="tgn,7011022">Parnassus</placeName>; but he does not say who rescued the child and
		conveyed him thither. According to Sophocles and Euripides, it was an old retainer of the
		family who thus saved Orestes, but Sophocles says that the old man had received the child
		from the hands of Electra. Hyginus, in agreement with Apollodorus, relates how, after the
		murder of Agamemnon, Electra took charge of （<foreign
			lang="la">sustulit</foreign>） her infant brother Orestes and committed him to the care
		of Strophius in <placeName
			authname="tgn,4003963"
			key="tgn,4003963">Phocis</placeName>.</note>
	<note>This vengeance for the murder of Agamemnon is the theme of three extant Greek tragedies,
		the <title>Choephori</title> of Aeschylus, the <title>Electra</title> of Sophocles, and the
			<title>Electra</title> of Euripides. It was related by Hagias in his epic, the
			<title>Returns</title>, as we learn from the brief summary of Proclus （<bibl
			default="NO">Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p. 53</bibl>）. Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Pind. P. 11"
			valid="yes">Pind. P. 11.36ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 119</bibl>. Homer briefly mentions the murder of Aegisthus by
		Orestes （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 1.29"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 1.29ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 1.298"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 1.298-300</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 3.306"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 3.306ff.</bibl>）; he does not expressly mention, but darkly hints
		at, the murder of Clytaemnestra by her son （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 3.309"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 3.309ff.</bibl>）.</note>
	<note>The trial and acquittal of Orestes in the court of the Areopagus at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Athens"
			key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> is the subject of Aeschylus's tragedy, the
			<title>Eumenides</title>, where the poet similarly represents the matricide as acquitted
		because the votes were equal (<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aesch. Eum. 752"
			valid="yes">Aesch. Eum. 752ff.</bibl>). The <title>Parian Chronicle</title> also records
		the acquittal on the same ground, and dates it in the reign of Demophon, king of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Athens"
			key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. See <bibl
			default="NO">Marmor Parium 40ff. (Fragmenta Historicorum Graecorum, ed. C. Müller,
			i.546)</bibl>. Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. IT 940"
			valid="yes">Eur. IT 940-967</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. IT 1469"
			valid="yes">Eur. IT 1469-1472</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Orest. 1648"
			valid="yes">Eur. Or. 1648-1652</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 1374</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 1.28.5"
			valid="yes">Paus. 1.28.5</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 8.34.4"
			valid="yes">Paus. 8.34.4</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis vi.4</bibl>. In the <title>Eumenides</title> the accusers
		of Orestes are the Furies. According to the Parian Chronicler, it was Erigone, the daughter
		of Aegisthus and Clytaemnestra, who instituted the prosecution for the murder of her father;
		the chronicler does not mention the murder of Clytaemnestra as an article in the indictment
		of Orestes. According to <bibl
			default="NO">the author of the Etymologicum Magnum, s.v. <foreign
				lang="greek">*ai)w/ra</foreign>, p. 42</bibl>, the prosecution was conducted at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Athens"
			key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> jointly by Erigone and her grandfather
		Tyndareus, and when it failed, Erigone hanged herself. Peloponnesian antiquaries, reported
		by <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 8.34.4"
			valid="yes">Paus. 8.34.4</bibl>, alleged that the accuser was not Tyndareus, who was
		dead, but Perilaus, a cousin of Clytaemnestra. According to <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 119</bibl>, Orestes was accused by Tyndareus before the
		people of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Mycenae"
			key="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>, but was suffered to retire into banishment
		for the sake of his father. As to the madness of Orestes, caused by the Furies of his
		murdered mother, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Orest. 931"
			valid="yes">Eur. Or. 931ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 3.22.1"
			valid="yes">Paus. 3.22.1</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 8.34.1"
			valid="yes">Paus. 8.34.1-4</bibl>. The incipient symptoms of madness, showing themselves
		immediately after the commission of the crime, are finely described by <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Aesch. Lib. 1021"
			valid="yes">Aesch. Lib. 1021ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>As to the oracle, compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. IT 77"
			valid="yes">Eur. IT 77-92</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. IT 970"
			valid="yes">Eur. IT 970-978</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 1374</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 120</bibl>.</note>
	<note>The Taurians inhabited the <placeName
			authname="tgn,1003381"
			key="tgn,1003381">Crimea</placeName>. As to their custom of sacrificing castaways and
		strangers, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hdt. 4.103"
			valid="yes">Hdt. 4.103</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. IT 34"
			valid="yes">Eur. IT 34-41</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Diod. 4.44.7</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 1.43.1"
			valid="yes">Paus. 1.43.1</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Orphica, Argon. 1075ff., ed Abel</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Ovid, Ex Ponto iii.2.45-58</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Mela ii.11</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Ammianus Marcellinus xxii.8.34</bibl>. According to Herodotus, these
		Taurians sacrificed human beings to a Virgin Goddess, whom they identified with Iphigenia,
		daughter of Agamemnon. The victims were shipwrecked persons and any Greeks on whom they
		could lay hands. They were slaughtered by being knocked on the head with a club, after which
		their heads were set up on stakes and their bodies thrown down a precipice into the sea or
		buried in the ground; for reports differed in regard to the disposal of the corpses, though
		all agreed as to the setting of the heads on stakes. Ammianus Marcellinus says that the
		native name of the goddess was Orsiloche.</note>
	<note>This account of the disposal of the bodies of the victims is based on <cit>
			<bibl
				default="NO"
				n="Eur. IT 625"
				valid="yes">Eur. IT 625ff.:—</bibl>
			<quote
				lang="greek"
				type="drama">
				<sp>
					<speaker>*)ore/sths</speaker>
					<l>ta/fos de\ poi=os de/cetai/ m', o(/tan qa/nw;</l>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>*)ifige/neia</speaker>
					<l>pu=r i(ero\n e)/ndon xa/sma t' eu)rwpo\n pe/tras.</l>
				</sp>
			</quote>
		</cit>Compare <cit>
			<bibl
				default="NO"
				n="Eur. IT 1154"
				valid="yes">Eur. IT 1154ff.:—</bibl>
			<quote
				type="drama">
				<l>h)/dh tw=n ce/nwn kath/rcato,</l>
				<l>a)du/tois t' e)n a(gnoi=s sw=ma la/mpontai puri/;</l>
			</quote>
		</cit>Thus Apollodorus differs from the account which Herodotus gives of the disposal of the
		bodies. See the preceding note.</note>
	<note>This account of the expedition of Orestes and Pylades to the land of the Taurians, and
		their escape with the image of Artemis, is the subject of Euripides's play <title>Iphigenia
			in Tauris</title>, which Apollodorus seems to have followed closely. The gist of the
		play is told in verse by <bibl
			default="NO">Ovid, Ex Ponto iii.2.43-96</bibl> and in prose by <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 120</bibl>. Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 1374</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. pp. 7, 141ff. (First
			Vatican Mythographer 20; Second Vatican Mythographer 202)</bibl>.</note>
	<note>In saying that the image of the Tauric Artemis was taken to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Athens"
			key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> our author follows Euripides. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. IT 89"
			valid="yes">Eur. IT 89-91</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. IT 1212"
			valid="yes">Eur. IT 1212-1214</bibl>. But according to Euripides the image was not to
		remain in <placeName
			authname="perseus,Athens"
			key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> but to be carried to a sacred place in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002681"
			key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> called <placeName
			authname="tgn,5004271"
			key="tgn,5004271">Halae</placeName>, where it was to be set up in a temple specially
		built for it and to be called the image of Artemis Tauropolus or Brauronian Artemis （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. IT 1446"
			valid="yes">Eur. IT 1446-1467</bibl>）. An old wooden image of Artemis, which purported
		to be the one brought from the land of the Taurians, was shown at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Brauron"
			key="perseus,Brauron">Brauron</placeName> in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002681"
			key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> as late as the second century of our era; Iphigenia
		is said to have landed with the image at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Brauron"
			key="perseus,Brauron">Brauron</placeName> and left it there, while she herself went on
		by land to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Athens"
			key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and afterwards to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Argos"
			key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 1.23.7"
			valid="yes">Paus. 1.23.7</bibl>, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 1.33.1"
			valid="yes">Paus. 1.33.1</bibl>. But according to some the original image was carried
		off by Xerxes to <placeName
			authname="tgn,7017509"
			key="tgn,7017509">Susa</placeName>, and was afterwards presented by Seleucus to <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002280"
			key="tgn,7002280">Laodicea</placeName> in <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000140"
			key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>, where it was said to remain down to the time of
		Pausanias in the second century of our era （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 3.16.8"
			valid="yes">Paus. 3.16.8</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 8.46.3"
			valid="yes">Paus. 8.46.3</bibl>）. Euripides has recorded, in the form of prophecy, two
		interesting features in the ritual of Artemis at <placeName
			authname="tgn,5004271"
			key="tgn,5004271">Halae</placeName> or <placeName
			authname="perseus,Brauron"
			key="perseus,Brauron">Brauron</placeName>. In sacrificing to the goddess the priest drew
		blood with a sword from the throat of a man, and this was regarded as a substitute for the
		sacrifice of Orestes, of which the goddess had been defrauded by his escape. Such a custom
		is explained most naturally as a mitigation of an older practice of actually sacrificing
		human beings to the goddess; and the tradition of such sacrifices at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Brauron"
			key="perseus,Brauron">Brauron</placeName> would suffice to give rise to the story that
		the image of the cruel goddess had been brought from the land of ferocious barbarians on the
		Black Sea. For similar mitigations of an old custom of human sacrifice, see <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Dying God</title>, pp. 214ff.</bibl> The other feature in the
		ritual at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Brauron"
			key="perseus,Brauron">Brauron</placeName> which Euripides notices was that the garments
		of women dying in child-bed used to be dedicated to Iphigenia, who was believed to be buried
		at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Brauron"
			key="perseus,Brauron">Brauron</placeName>. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. IT 1458"
			valid="yes">Eur. IT 1458-1467</bibl>. As to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Brauron"
			key="perseus,Brauron">Brauron</placeName> and <placeName
			authname="tgn,5004271"
			key="tgn,5004271">Halae</placeName>, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 1.33.1"
			valid="yes">Paus. 1.33.1</bibl> with <bibl
			default="NO">Frazer's note （vol. ii. pp. 445ff.）</bibl>. But other places besides <placeName
			authname="perseus,Brauron"
			key="perseus,Brauron">Brauron</placeName> claimed to possess the ancient idol of the
		Tauric Artemis. The wooden image of Artemis Orthia at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Sparta"
			key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, at whose altar the Spartan youths were scourged
		to the effusion of blood, was supposed by the Lacedaemonians to be the true original image
		brought by Iphigenia herself to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Sparta"
			key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>; and their claim was preferred by Pausanias to
		that of the Athenians （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 3.16.7"
			valid="yes">Paus. 3.16.7-10</bibl>）. Others said that Orestes and Iphigenia carried the
		image, hidden in a bundle of faggots, to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Aricia"
			key="perseus,Aricia">Aricia</placeName> in <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000080"
			key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>. See <bibl
			default="NO">Servius on Virgil, ii.116, vi.136</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scriptores rerum mythicarum Latini, ed. Bode, i. pp. 7, 142 (First Vatican
			Mythographer 20; Second Vatican Mythographer 202)</bibl>; compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 5.3.12"
			valid="yes">Strab. 5.3.12</bibl>. Indeed, it was affirmed by some people that on his
		wanderings Orestes had deposited, not one, but many images of Artemis in many places （<bibl
			default="NO">Aelius Lampridius, Heliogabalus 7）</bibl>. Such stories have clearly no
		historical value. In every case they were probably devised to explain or excuse a cruel and
		bloody ritual by deriving it from a barbarous country.</note>
	<note>This drifting of Orestes to <placeName
			authname="tgn,7011266"
			key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> seems to be mentioned by no other ancient writer.
		The verb （<foreign
			lang="greek">kaqosiwqh=nai）</foreign>, which I have taken to refer to the image and have
		translated by “dedicated,” may perhaps refer to Orestes; if so, it would mean “purified”
		from the guilt of matricide. According to <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 120</bibl>, Orestes sailed with Iphigenia and Pylades to the
		island of Sminthe, which is otherwise unknown. Another place to which Orestes and Iphigenia
		were supposed to have come on their way from the <placeName
			authname="tgn,1003381"
			key="tgn,1003381">Crimea</placeName> was <placeName
			authname="perseus,Comana Cappadociae"
			key="perseus,Comana Cappadociae">Comana</placeName> in <placeName
			authname="tgn,6003016"
			key="tgn,6003016">Cappadocia</placeName>; there he was said to have introduced the
		worship of Artemis Tauropolus and to have shorn his hair in token of mourning. Hence the
		city was said to derive its name （<foreign
			lang="greek">*ko/mana</foreign> from <foreign
			lang="greek">ko/mh）.</foreign> See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 12.2.3"
			valid="yes">Strab. 12.2.3</bibl>. According to <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 1374</bibl>, Orestes was driven by storms
		to that part of <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000140"
			key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> where <placeName
			authname="tgn,6005333"
			key="tgn,6005333">Seleucia</placeName> and <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002354"
			key="tgn,7002354">Antioch</placeName> afterwards stood; and Mount Amanus, on the borders
		of <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000140"
			key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> and <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002470"
			key="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName>, was so named because there the matricide was
		relieved of his madness （<foreign
			lang="greek">*)amano/s</foreign>, from <foreign
			lang="greek">mani/a</foreign>“madness” and <foreign
			lang="greek">a)</foreign> privative）. Such is a sample of Byzantine etymology.</note>
	<note>As to the marriage of Electra to Pylades, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. El. 1249"
			valid="yes">Eur. El. 1249</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Orest. 1658"
			valid="yes">Eur. Or. 1658ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 122</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the marriage of Orestes and Hermione, see above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. Epit. E.5.14"
			valid="yes">Apollod. E.5.14</bibl>, with the note. According to <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 2.18.6"
			valid="yes">Paus. 2.18.6</bibl>, Orestes had by Hermione a son Tisamenus, who succeeded
		his father on the throne of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Sparta"
			key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. But Pausanias also mentions a tradition that
		Orestes had a bastard son Penthilus by Erigone, daughter of Aegisthus, and for this
		tradition he cites as his authority the old epic poet Cinaethon. Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 1474</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Compare Scholiast on <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Orest. 1645"
			valid="yes">Eur. Or. 1645</bibl>, quoting Asclepiades as his authority; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 1374</bibl>. In the passage of Euripides on
		which the Scholiast comments （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Orest. 1643"
			valid="yes">Eur. Or. 1643-1647</bibl>）, Orestes is bidden by Apollo to retire to <placeName
			authname="tgn,7017080"
			key="tgn,7017080">Parrhasia</placeName>, a district of <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002735"
			key="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>, for the space of a year, after which he is to go
		and stand his trial for the murder of his mother at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Athens"
			key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. This year to be spent in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002735"
			key="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName> is no doubt the year of banishment to which
		homicides had to submit before they were allowed to resume social intercourse with their
		fellows. See <bibl
			default="NO">Frazer's note above on Apollod. 2.5.11 （vol. i. pp. 218ff.</bibl>）. The
		period is so interpreted by a <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Eur. Or. 1645</bibl>. As to Oresteum in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002735"
			key="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 8.3.1"
			valid="yes">Paus. 8.3.1ff.</bibl>, who says that it was formerly called Oresthasium. A
		curious story of the madness of Orestes in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002735"
			key="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName> is told by <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 8.34.1"
			valid="yes">Paus. 8.34.1-4</bibl>. He says that, when the Furies were about to drive him
		mad, they appeared to him black, but that he bit off one of his own fingers, whereupon they
		appeared to him white, and he immediately recovered his wits. The grave of Orestes was near <placeName
			authname="perseus,Tegea"
			key="perseus,Tegea">Tegea</placeName> in <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002735"
			key="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>; from there his bones were stolen by a Spartan and
		carried to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Sparta"
			key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> in compliance with an oracle, which assured the
		Spartans of victory over their stubborn foes the Tegeans, if only they could get possession
		of these valuable relics. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hdt. 1.67"
			valid="yes">Hdt. 1.67ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 3.3.5"
			valid="yes">Paus. 3.3.5ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 3.11.10"
			valid="yes">Paus. 3.11.10</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 8.54.3"
			valid="yes">Paus. 8.54.3</bibl>.</note>
	<note>For the wanderings of Menelaus on the voyage from <placeName
			authname="perseus,Troy"
			key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 3.276"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 3.276-302</bibl>; compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.25.2"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.25.2</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the real and the phantom Helen, see above, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. Epit. E.3.5"
			valid="yes">Apollod. E.3.5</bibl>, with the note.</note>
	<note>The return of Menelaus to his home was related by Hagias in the <title>Returns</title>, as
		we learn from the brief abstract of that poem by <bibl
			default="NO">Proclus in Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, p.
		53</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Homer in the <title>Odyssey</title> （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 4.561"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 4.561-569</bibl>） represents Proteus prophesying to Menelaus that
		he was fated not to die but to be transported by the gods to the Elysian Fields, there to
		dwell at ease where there was neither snow, nor storm, or rain, because he had married Helen
		and was thereby a in-law of Zeus. Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Eur. Hel. 1676"
			valid="yes">Eur. Hel. 1676-1679</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the adventures of Ulysses with the Cicones, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 9.39"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 9.39-66</bibl>. The Cicones were a Thracian tribe; Xerxes and his
		army marched through their country （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hdt. 7.110"
			valid="yes">Hdt. 7.110</bibl>）. As to Maro, the priest of Apollo at Ismarus, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 9.196"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 9.196-211</bibl>. He dwelt in a wooded grove of Apollo, and
		bestowed splendid presents and twelve jars of red honey-sweet wine, in return for the
		protection which he and his wife received at the hands of Ulysses.</note>
	<note>As to the adventures of Ulysses with the Lotus-eaters, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 9.82"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 9.82-104</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125</bibl>. The Lotus-eaters were a tribe of northern <placeName
			authname="tgn,7001242"
			key="tgn,7001242">Africa</placeName>, inhabiting the coast of <placeName
			authname="perseus,Tripolis"
			key="perseus,Tripolis">Tripolis</placeName> （<bibl
			default="NO">Scylax, Periplus 110</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Pliny, Nat. Hist. v.28</bibl>）. As to the lotus, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hdt. 4.177"
			valid="yes">Hdt. 4.177</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Polybius xii.2.1, quoted by Athenaeus xiv.65, p. 651 DF</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Theophrastus, Hist. Plant. iv.3.1ff.</bibl> The tree is the Zizyphus Lotus
		of the botanists. Theophrastus says that the tree was common in <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000172"
			key="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>, that is, in northern <placeName
			authname="tgn,7001242"
			key="tgn,7001242">Africa</placeName>, and that an army marching on <placeName
			authname="perseus,Carthage"
			key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> subsisted on its fruit alone for several
		days. The modern name of the tree is <foreign
			lang="berber">ssodr</foreign> or <foreign
			lang="berber">ssidr</foreign>. A whole district in <placeName
			authname="perseus,Tripolis"
			key="perseus,Tripolis">Tripolis</placeName> is named Ssodria after it. See <bibl
			default="NO">A. Wiedemann, <title>Herodots Zweites Buch</title>, p. 385, note on
			Herodotus, ii.96</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the adventures of Ulysses and his companions among the Cyclopes, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 9.105"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 9.105-542</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125</bibl>. The story is a folk-tale found in many lands. See
		Frazer's Appendix to Apollodorus, “Ulysses and Polyphemus.”</note>
	<note>As to the adventures of Ulysses with Aeolus, the Keeper of the Winds, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 10.1"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 10.1-76</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Ov. Met. 14.223"
			valid="yes">Ov. Met. 14.223-232</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Homer says （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 10.30"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 10.30</bibl>） they were so near land that they could already see
		the men tending the fires （<foreign
			lang="greek">purpole/ontas</foreign>）; but whether the fires were signals to guide the
		ship to port, or watchfires of shepherds tending their flocks on the hills, does not
		appear.</note>
	<note>As to the adventures of Ulysses and his comrades among the Laestrygones, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 10.80"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 10.80-132</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Ov. Met. 14.233"
			valid="yes">Ov. Met. 14.233-244</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the adventures of Ulysses and his comrades with the enchantress Circe, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 10.133"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 10.133-574</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Ov. Met. 14.246"
			valid="yes">Ov. Met. 14.246-440</bibl>. The word （<foreign
			lang="greek">fa/rmaka</foreign>） here translated “enchantments” means primarily drugs;
		but in the early stages of medicine drugs were supposed to be endowed with magical potency,
		partly in virtue of the spells, that is, the form of words, with which the medical
		practitioner administered them to the patient. Hence druggist and enchanter were nearly
		synonymous terms. As Circe used her knowledge of drugs purely for magical purposes, without
		any regard to the medical side of the profession, it seems better to translate her <foreign
			lang="greek">fa/rmaka</foreign> by “enchantments” or “charms” rather than “drugs,” and
		to call her an enchantress instead of a druggist.</note>
	<note>In <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 10.237"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 10.237ff.</bibl>） the companions of Ulysses are turned into swine
		only; nothing is said about a transformation of them into wolves, lions, and asses, though
		round about the house of the enchantress they saw wolves and lions, which stood on their
		hind legs, wagged their tails, and fawned upon them, because they were men enchanted （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 10.210"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 10.210-219</bibl>）.</note>
	<note>As to moly, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 10.302"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 10.302-306</bibl>. Homer says that it was a plant dug up from the
		earth, with a black root and a white flower. According to <bibl
			default="NO">Theophrastus, Hist. Plant. ix.15.7</bibl>, moly resembled <foreign
			lang="la">Allium nigrum</foreign>, which was found in the valley of Pheneus and on Mount
		Cyllene in northern <placeName
			authname="tgn,7002735"
			key="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>; he says it had a round root, like an onion, and a
		leaf like a squill, and that it was used as an antidote to spells and enchantments. But
		probably the moly of Homer grew on no earthly hill or valley, but only in “fairyland
		forlorn.”</note>
	<note>Telegonus is unknown to Homer, who mentions no offspring of Ulysses by the enchantress
		Circe. He is named as a son of Ulysses and Circe by Hesiod in a line which is suspected,
		however, of being spurious （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hes. Th. 1014"
			valid="yes">Hes. Th. 1014</bibl>）. He was recognized by Hagias in his epic, <title>The
			Returns</title>, and by another Cyclic poet Eugammon of <placeName
			authname="tgn,7000639"
			key="tgn,7000639">Cyrene</placeName>; indeed Eugammon composed an epic called the
			<title>Telegony</title> on the adventures of Telegonus, but according to him Telegonus
		was a son of Ulysses by Calypso, not by Circe. See <bibl
			default="NO">Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, pp. 56, 57ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Od. xvi.118, p. 1796</bibl>. According to <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125</bibl>, Ulysses had two sons, Nausithous and Telegonus,
		by Circe. As to Telegonus, see also below, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. Epit. E.7.36"
			valid="yes">Apollod. E.7.36ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>The visit of Ulysses to the land of the dead is the theme of the eleventh book of the
			<title>Odyssey</title>. Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125</bibl>. The visit was the subject of one of the two great
		pictures by Polygnotus at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Delphi"
			key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 10.28"
			valid="yes">Paus. 10.28-31</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the consultation with Tiresias, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 11.90"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11.90-151</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the interview of Ulysses with his mother, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 11.153"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11.153-224</bibl>.</note>
	<note>In the hot air of Circe's enchanted isle Elpenor had slept for coolness on the roof of the
		palace; then, suddenly wakened by the noise and bustle of his comrades making ready to
		depart, he started up and, forgetting to descend by the ladder, tumbled from the roof and
		broke his neck. In his hurry to be off, Ulysses had not stayed to bury his dead comrade; so
		the soul of Elpenor, unwept and unburied, was the first to meet his captain on the threshold
		of the spirit land. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 10.552"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 10.552-560</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 11.51"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11.51-83</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the return of Ulysses to the isle of Circe, and his sailing past the Sirens, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.1"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.1-200</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125</bibl>. Homer does not name the Sirens individually nor
		mention their parentage, but by using the dual in reference to them （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.52"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.52</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.167"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.167</bibl>） he indicates that they were two in number.
		Sophocles, in his play <title>Ulysses</title>, called the Sirens daughters of Phorcus, and
		agreed with Homer in recognizing only two of them. See <bibl
			default="NO">Plut. Quaest. Conviv. ix.14.6</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, iii.66, frag.
			861</bibl>. Apollonius Rhodius says that the Muse Terpsichore bore the Sirens to
		Achelous （<bibl
			default="NO">Ap. Rhod., Argon. iv.895ff.</bibl>）. Hyginus names four of them, Teles,
		Raidne, Molpe, and Thelxiope （<bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. praefat. p. 30, ed. Bunte</bibl>）, and, in agreement with
		Apollodorus, says that they were the offspring of Achelous by the Muse Melpomene. Tzetzes
		calls them Parthenope, Leucosia, and Ligia, but adds that other people named them Pisinoe,
		Aglaope, and Thelxiepia, and that they were the children of Achelous and Terpsichore. With
		regard to the parts which they took in the bewitching concert, he agrees with Apollodorus.
		See <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 712</bibl>. According to a <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Ap. Rhod., Argon.iv.892</bibl>, their names were Thelxiope, or
		Thelxione, Molpe, and Aglaophonus. As to their names and parents see also <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Od. 12. p. 1709</bibl>, <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Od. xii.39</bibl>, who mention the view that the father
		of the Sirens was Achelous, and that their mother was either the Muse Terpsichore, or
		Sterope, daughter of Porthaon.</note>
	<note>Similarly Apollonius Rhodius （<bibl
			default="NO">Ap. Rhod., Argon. iv.898ff.</bibl>） describes the Sirens as partly virgins
		and partly birds. Aelian tells us （<bibl
			default="NO">Ael., Nat. Anim. xvii.23</bibl>） that poets and painters represented them
		as winged maidens with the feet of birds. Ovid says that the Sirens had the feet and
		feathers of birds, but the faces of virgins; and he asks why these daughters of Achelous, as
		he calls them, had this hybrid form. Perhaps, he thinks, it was because they had been
		playing with Persephone when gloomy Dis carried her off, and they had begged the gods to
		grant them wings, that they might search for their lost playmate over seas as well as land.
		See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Ov. Met. 5.552"
			valid="yes">Ov. Met. 5.552-562</bibl>. In like manner Hyginus describes the Sirens as
		women above and fowls below, but he says that their wings and feathers were a punishment
		inflicted on them by Demeter for not rescuing Persephone from the clutches of Pluto. See <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125, 141</bibl>. Another story was that they were maidens
		whom Aphrodite turned into birds because they chose to remain unmarried. See <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Od. 12.47, p. 1709</bibl>. It is said that they once
		vied with the Muses in singing, and that the Muses, being victorious, plucked off the
		Siren's feathers and made crowns out of them for themselves （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 9.34.3"
			valid="yes">Paus. 9.34.3</bibl>）. In ancient art, as in literature, the Sirens are
		commonly represented as women above and birds below. See <bibl
			default="NO">Miss J. E. Harrison, <title>Myths of the Odyssey</title> （London, 1882）,
			pp. 146ff.</bibl> Homer says nothing as to the semi-bird shape of the Sirens, thus
		leaving us to infer that they were purely human.</note>
	<note>This is not mentioned by Homer, but is affirmed by <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125, 141</bibl>）. Others said that the Sirens cast themselves
		into the sea and were drowned from sheer vexation at the escape of Ulysses. See <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. Od.xii.39</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Od. 12.167, p. 1709</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 712</bibl>; compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Strab. 6.1.1"
			valid="yes">Strab. 6.1.1</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to Ulysses and the Wandering Rocks, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.52"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.52-72</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.201"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.201-221</bibl>. The poet mentions （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.70"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.70-72</bibl>） the former passage of the Argo between the
		Wandering or Clashing Rocks, as to which see above <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. 1.9.22"
			valid="yes">Apollod. 1.9.22</bibl>, with the note. It has been suggested that in the
		story of the Wandering Rocks we have a confused reminiscence of some sailor's story of
		floating icebergs. See <bibl
			default="NO">Merry, on Homer, Od. xii.61</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the passage of Ulysses between Scylla and Charybdis, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.73"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.73-126</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.222"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.222-259</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125, 199</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Homer mentions Crataeis as the mother of Scylla, but says nothing as to her father （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.124"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.124ff.</bibl>）. According to Stesichorus, the mother of Scylla
		was Lamia. See Scholiast on <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.124"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.124</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Od. xii.85, p. 1714</bibl>. Apollonius Rhodius
		represents Scylla as a daughter of Phorcus by the night-wandering hag Hecate （<bibl
			default="NO">Ap. Rhod., Argon. iv.828ff.</bibl>）, and this parentage has the support of
		Acusilaus, except that he named her father Phorcys instead of Phorcus （<bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Ap. Rhod., Argon. iv.828</bibl>; compare <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Od. xii.85, p. 1714</bibl>）. Hyginus calls her a
		daughter of Typhon and Echidna （<bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125, 151, and praefat. p. 31, ed. Bunte</bibl>）. A <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Plat. Rep. 9, 588c</bibl>, who may have copied the present
		passage of Apollodorus, calls Scylla a daughter of Crataeis and Tyrrhenus or Phorcus, adding
		that she had the face and breasts of a woman, but from the flanks six heads of dogs and
		twelve feet. Some said that the father of Scylla was Triton （<bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Od. xii.85, p. 1714</bibl>）; and perhaps the name Triton
		should be read instead of Trienus in the present passage of Apollodorus. See the Critical
		Note.</note>
	<note>As to the adventures of Ulysses in Thrinacia, the island of the Sun, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.127"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.127-141</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.260"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.260-402</bibl>.</note>
	<note>See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.403"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.403-425</bibl>.</note>
	<note>See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.426"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.426-450</bibl>, compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 5.128"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 5.128-135</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the stay of Ulysses with Calypso in the island of Ogygia, and his departure in a
		boat of his own building, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 5.13"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 5.13-281</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 7.243"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 7.243-266</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125</bibl>. According to <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 7.259"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 7.259</bibl>, Ulysses stayed seven years with Calypso, not five
		years, as Apollodorus says. Hyginus limits the stay to one year. Homer does not mention that
		Calypso bore a son to Ulysses. In the <title>Theogony</title> of Hesiod （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hes. Th. 1111"
			valid="yes">Hes. Th. 1111ff.</bibl>） it is said that Circe （not Calypso）, bore two sons,
		Agrius and Latinus, to Ulysses; the verses, however, are probably not by Hesiod but have
		been interpolated by a later poet of the Roman era in order to provide the Latins with a
		distinguished Greek ancestry. The verses are quoted by the <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Ap. Rhod., Argon. iii.200</bibl>. Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Joannes Lydus, De mensibus i.13, p. 7, ed. Bekker</bibl>. Eustathius says （<bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Od. xvi.118, p. 1796</bibl>） that, according to Hesiod,
		Ulysses had two sons, Agrius and Latinus, by Circe, and two sons, Nausithous and Nausinous,
		by Calypso.</note>
	<note>See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 5.282"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 5.282-493</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125</bibl>.</note>
	<note>See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 6"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 6</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 7"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 7</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 8"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 8</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.1"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.1-124</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 125</bibl>.</note>
	<note>See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.125"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12.125-187</bibl>. “Poseidon does not propose to bury the city, but
		to shut it off from the use of its two harbours （cp. <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 6.263"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 6.263</bibl>） by some great mountain mass” （<bibl
			default="NO">Merry on Hom. Od. 12.152</bibl>）.</note>
	<note>The number of the suitors, according to Homer, was one hundred and eight, namely,
		fifty-two from Dulichium, twenty-four from Same, twenty from <placeName
			authname="tgn,7011374"
			key="tgn,7011374">Zacynthus</placeName>, and twelve from <placeName
			authname="tgn,1007519"
			key="tgn,1007519">Ithaca</placeName>. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 16.245"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 16.245-253</bibl>. Apollodorus gives the numbers from these islands
		as fifty-seven, twenty-three, forty-four, and twelve respectively, or a hundred and
		thirty-six in all. Homer does not give a regular list of the names, but mentions some of
		them incidentally.</note>
	<note>As to the reckless waste of the suitors, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 14.80"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 14.80-109</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to Penelope's web, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 19.136"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 19.136-158</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 126</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the meeting of Ulysses and Eumaeus, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 14.1"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 14.1-492</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 126</bibl>.</note>
	<note>As to the meeting and recognition of Ulysses and Telemachus, see <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 16.1"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 16.1-234</bibl>.</note>
	<note>See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 17.184"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 17.184-253</bibl>.</note>
	<note>See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 17.360"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 17.360-457</bibl>.</note>
	<note>See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 18.1"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 18.1-107</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 126</bibl>. In Homer it is in a boxing-match, not in a
		wrestling-bout, that Ulysses vanquishes the braggart beggar Irus. Hyginus, like Apollodorus,
		substitutes wrestling for boxing.</note>
	<note>See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 21.188"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 21.188-244</bibl>.</note>
	<note>See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 21.1"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 21.1-82</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 126</bibl>.</note>
	<note>See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 21.140"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 21.140-434</bibl>, <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 22.1"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 22.1-389</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 126</bibl>.</note>
	<note>See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 22.417"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 22.417-477</bibl>.</note>
	<note>See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 22.153"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 22.153-297</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 24.205"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 24.205-348</bibl>.</note>
	<note>Tiresias had warned Ulysses that, after slaying the suitors, he must journey inland till
		he came to a country where men knew not the sea, and where a wayfarer would mistake for a
		winnowing-fan the oar which Ulysses was carrying on his shoulder. There Ulysses was to
		sacrifice a ram, a bull, and a boar to Poseidon, the god whom he had offended. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 11.119"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11.119-131</bibl>. But the journey itself and the sacrifice are not
		recorded by Homer. In a little island off Cos a Greek skipper told Dr. W. H. D. Rouse a
		similar story about the journey inland of the prophet Elias. The prophet, according to this
		account, was a fisherman who, long buffeted by storms, conceived a horror of the sea, and,
		putting an oar on his shoulder, took to the hills and walked till he met a man who did not
		know what an oar was. There the prophet planted his oar in the ground, and there he resolved
		to abide. That is why all the prophet's chapels are on the tops of hills. This legend was
		published by Dr. Rouse in <title>The Cambridge Review</title> under the heading of “A Greek
		skipper.” This and the remaining part of Apollodorus are probably drawn from the epic poem
			<title>Telegony</title>, a work by Eugammon of <placeName
			authname="tgn,7000639"
			key="tgn,7000639">Cyrene</placeName>, of which a short abstract by Proclus has been
		preserved. See <bibl
			default="NO">Epicorum Graecorum Fragmenta, ed. G. Kinkel, pp. 57ff.</bibl> The author of
		the abstract informs us that after the death and burial of the suitors “Ulysses sacrificed
		to the nymphs and sailed to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Elis"
			key="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName> to inspect the herds. And he was entertained by
		Polyxenus and received a present of a bowl. And after that followed the episodes of
		Trophonius, and Agamedes, and Augeas. Then he sailed home to <placeName
			authname="tgn,1007519"
			key="tgn,1007519">Ithaca</placeName> and offered the sacrifices prescribed by Tiresias.
		And after these things he went to the Thesprotians and married Callidice, queen of the
		Thesprotians. Then the Thesprotians made war on the Brygians, under the leadership of
		Ulysses. There Ares put Ulysses and his people to flight, and Athena engaged him in battle;
		but Apollo reconciled them. And after Callidice's death, Polypoetes, son of Ulysses,
		succeeded to the kingdom, and Ulysses himself went to <placeName
			authname="tgn,1007519"
			key="tgn,1007519">Ithaca</placeName>. Meanwhile Telegonus, sailing in search of his
		father, landed in <placeName
			authname="tgn,1007519"
			key="tgn,1007519">Ithaca</placeName> and ravaged the island; and marching out to repel
		him Ulysses was killed by his son in ignorance. Recognizing his error, Telegonus transported
		his father's body, and Telemachus, and Penelope to his mother, and she made them immortal.
		And Telegonus married Penelope, and Telemachus married Circe.” The tradition, mentioned also
		by <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 127</bibl>, that one son of Ulysses （Telegonus） married his
		father's widow （Penelope）, and that another son （Telemachus） married his father's concubine
		（Circe）, is very remarkable, and may possibly point to an old custom according to which a
		son inherited his father's wives and concubines, with the exception of his own mother.
		Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Apollod. 2.7.7"
			valid="yes">Apollod. 2.7.7</bibl>, with <bibl
			default="NO">Frazer's note （vol. i. p. 269）</bibl>. Apollodorus mentions the marriage of
		Telegonus to Penelope （see below）, but not the marriage of Telemachus to Circe.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 8.12.6"
			valid="yes">Paus. 8.12.6</bibl>, from whom we learn that the birth of this son
		Poliporthes or Ptoliporthes, as Pausanias calls him, was mentioned in the epic poem
			<title>Thesprotis</title>.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Oppian, Halieut. ii.497-500</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholia Graeca in Homeri Odysseam, ed. G. Dindorf, vol. i. p. 6</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 11.134"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11.134</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Eustathius on Hom. Od. xi.133, p. 1676</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Philostratus, Vit. Apollon. vi.32</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Philostratus, Her. iii.42</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Parthenius, Narrat. 3</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 794</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Aristoph. Plutus 303</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Cicero, Tusc. Disp. ii.21.48ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hor. Carm. 3.29.8"
			valid="yes">Hor. Carm. 3.29.8</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Hyginus, Fab. 127</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Ovid, Ibis 567ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis vi.14ff.</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 2.44"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 2.44</bibl>. The fish （<foreign
			lang="greek">trugw/n</foreign>）, whose spine is said to have barbed the fatal spear, is
		the common stingray （<foreign
			lang="la">Trygon pastinaca</foreign>）, as I learn from Professor D'Arcy Wentworth
		Thompson, who informs me that the fish is abundant in the Mediterranean and not uncommon on
		our southern coasts. For ancient descriptions of the fish he refers me to <bibl
			default="NO">Oppian, Halieut. ii.470ff.</bibl> （the <foreign
			lang="la">locus classicus</foreign>）; <bibl
			default="NO">Ael., Nat. Anim. i.56</bibl>; <bibl
			default="NO">Nicander, Ther. 828ff.</bibl> According to Aelian, the wound inflicted by
		the stingray is incurable. Hercules is said to have lost one of his fingers by the bite of a
		stingray （<bibl
			default="NO">Ptolemy Hephaest., Nov. Hist. ii. in Westermann's Mythographi Graeci, p.
			184</bibl>）. Classical scholars, following Liddell and Scott, sometimes erroneously
		identify the fish with the roach. The death of Ulysses through the wound of a stingray is
		foreshadowed in the prophecy of Tiresias that his death would come from the sea （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 11.134"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11.134ff.</bibl>）. According to a <bibl
			default="NO">Scholiast on Hom. （Scholia Graeca in Homeri Odysseam, ed. G. Dindorf, vol.
			i. p. 6）</bibl>, Hyginus, and Dictys Cretensis, Ulysses had been warned by an oracle or
		a dream to beware of his son, who would kill him; accordingly, fearing to be slain by
		Telemachus, he banished him to Cephallenia （<bibl
			default="NO">Dictys Cretensis vi.14</bibl>）. But he forgot his son Telegonus, whom he
		had left behind with his mother Circe in her enchanted island. The death of Ulysses at the
		hands of his son Telegonus was the subject of a tragedy by Sophocles. See <bibl
			default="NO"><title>The Fragments of Sophocles</title>, ed. A. C. Pearson, vol. ii. pp.
			105ff.</bibl></note>
	<note>A high mound of earth was shown as the grave of Penelope at <placeName
			authname="perseus,Mantinea"
			key="perseus,Mantinea">Mantinea</placeName> in Arcadia. According to the Mantinean
		story, Ulysses had found her unfaithful and banished her the house; so she went first to her
		native <placeName
			authname="tgn,7011065"
			key="tgn,7011065">Sparta</placeName>, and afterwards to <placeName
			authname="perseus,Mantinea"
			key="perseus,Mantinea">Mantinea</placeName>, where she died and was buried. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Paus. 8.12.5"
			valid="yes">Paus. 8.12.5ff.</bibl> The tradition that Penelope was the mother of Pan by
		Hermes （Mercury） is mentioned by <bibl
			default="NO">Cicero, De natura deorum iii.22.56</bibl>. According to Duris, the Samian,
		Penelope was the mother of Pan by all the suitors （<bibl
			default="NO">Tzetzes, Scholiast on Lycophron 772</bibl>）. The same story is mentioned
		also by <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Serv. A. 2.44"
			valid="yes">Serv. Verg. A. 2.44</bibl>, who says that Penelope was supposed to have
		given birth to Pan during her husband's absence, and that when Ulysses came home and found
		the monstrous infant in the house, he fled and set out afresh on his wanderings.</note>
	<note>Amphinomus was one of the suitors of Penelope; his words pleased her more than those of
		the other suitors, because he had a good understanding. See <bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 16.394"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 16.394-398</bibl>. He was afterwards killed by Telemachus （<bibl
			default="NO"
			n="Hom. Od. 12.89"
			valid="yes">Hom. Od. 12. 89ff.</bibl>）. The suspicion that Penelope was unfaithful to
		her husband has no support in Homer.</note>
	<note>Compare <bibl
			default="NO">Plut. Quaest. Graec. 14</bibl>. According to Plutarch's account, the
		kinsmen of the slain suitors rose in revolt against Ulysses; but Neoptolemus, being invited
		by both parties to act as arbitrator, sentenced Ulysses to banishment for bloodshed, and
		condemned the friends and relatives of the suitors to pay an annual compensation to Ulysses
		for the damage they had done to his property. The sentence obliged Ulysses to withdraw not
		only from <placeName
			authname="tgn,1007519"
			key="tgn,1007519">Ithaca</placeName>, but also from Cephallenia and <placeName
			authname="tgn,7011374"
			key="tgn,7011374">Zacynthus</placeName>; and he retired to <placeName
			authname="tgn,1000080"
			key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>. The compensation exacted from the heirs of the
		suitors was paid in kind, and consisted of barley groats, wine, honey, olive oil, and animal
		victims of mature age. This payment Ulysses ordered to be made to his son Telemachus.</note>
	<note>These last recorded doings of Ulysses appear to be mentioned by no other ancient
		writer.</note>
</notes>
